<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- This is a WordPress eXtended RSS file generated by WordPress as an export of your site. -->
<!-- It contains information about your site's posts, pages, comments, categories, and other content. -->
<!-- You may use this file to transfer that content from one site to another. -->
<!-- This file is not intended to serve as a complete backup of your site. -->

<!-- To import this information into a WordPress site follow these steps: -->
<!-- 1. Log in to that site as an administrator. -->
<!-- 2. Go to Tools: Import in the WordPress admin panel. -->
<!-- 3. Install the "WordPress" importer from the list. -->
<!-- 4. Activate & Run Importer. -->
<!-- 5. Upload this file using the form provided on that page. -->
<!-- 6. You will first be asked to map the authors in this export file to users -->
<!--    on the site. For each author, you may choose to map to an -->
<!--    existing user on the site or to create a new user. -->
<!-- 7. WordPress will then import each of the posts, pages, comments, categories, etc. -->
<!--    contained in this file into your site. -->

<!-- generator="WordPress/4.3-alpha-32330" created="2015-05-01 22:20" -->
<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:excerpt="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/excerpt/"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/"
>

<channel>
	<title>Eclipseguy.com – Eclipse Chasing, Solar Eclipse Videos, Trip Reports, Galleries</title>
	<link>http://eclipseguy.com</link>
	<description>The Canadian Eclipse Chaser's home base on the internet</description>
	<pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 22:20:26 +0000</pubDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<wp:wxr_version>1.2</wp:wxr_version>
	<wp:base_site_url>http://eclipseguy.com</wp:base_site_url>
	<wp:base_blog_url>http://eclipseguy.com</wp:base_blog_url>

	<wp:author><wp:author_id>5</wp:author_id><wp:author_login>eclipseguy</wp:author_login><wp:author_email>imoon@eclipseguy.com</wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[eclipseguy]]></wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[David]]></wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[Makepeace]]></wp:author_last_name></wp:author>

	<wp:category><wp:term_id>6</wp:term_id><wp:category_nicename>tripreport</wp:category_nicename><wp:category_parent></wp:category_parent><wp:cat_name><![CDATA[Trip Report]]></wp:cat_name></wp:category>

	<generator>http://wordpress.org/?v=4.3-alpha-32330</generator>

	<item>
		<title>Baja Mexico - 11 July 1991</title>
		<link>http://eclipseguy.com/tripreport/total-solar-eclipse-11-july-1991-mexico</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 1991 04:00:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[eclipseguy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://eclipseguy.com/?p=668</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/mexico_logo.jpg" alt="main logo mexico 91" />

La Paz
BCS, Mexico
My first trip into the Shadow of the Moon</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">Eclipse chasers like to keep track of the amount of time they've spent inside the Moon's shadow. The number is expressed in seconds. I call mine my "UmbraLog" and I am currently enjoying number 1838 (or 30.633 minutes). The number is a bit of a status symbol and a point of achievement and pride amongst lifetime chasers.</p>

While a typical total eclipse might give you 2 or 3 minutes of totality, the event of 11 July 1991 turned out to be one of the longest eclipses of the century, plunging us all into almost 7 minutes of unearthly magic. Not bad for my first try.

Baja California Sur, Mexico, is the thin peninsula that extends south of the state of California along mainland Mexico's Pacific side. In the days leading up to the eclipse, the town of La Paz was flooded with scientists and chasers from around the globe transforming this sleepy coastal village into Astronomy Central.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/mexico_hats.jpg" alt="souvenirs_mexico" />

Eclipse souvenirs for sale on the streets of La Paz.</blockquote>
Mexico was well prepared for this event. The government spent lots of time and money to promote the eclipse and to manage the converging interests of thousands of people. And they did a great job. The official Mexico eclipse logo (at top of the page) was everywhere in the newspaper and on billboards, hats, T-shirts and pamphlets, and the local parades, dances and parties in the street in celebration of the eclipse went on for almost a week.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/mex_parade.jpg" alt="mex parade" />

The Mexicans know how to throw an eclipse party!</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/mex_scopeman.jpg" alt="scope guy" />

Many chasers arrived within the path of totality days in advance
to align and test their equipment.</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">The North American media always make a big deal of any eclipse that falls between its shores and this one was certainly no exception. In addition, numerous films were made about this eclipse including one feature film entitled "Eclipse" by Canadian filmmaker Jeremy Podeswa.</p>

<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/mex_spicer.jpg" alt="mex spicer" />

eclipseguy relaxes with "Eclipse" film cinematographer Michael Spicer in La Paz on 10 July 1991.</blockquote>
On the day of the eclipse, my friend, Amy, and I drove to the highest hilltop we could find in La Paz as the partial phases unfolded in the sky above our heads.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/mex_amylooks.jpg" alt="mex amy" />

Amy watches the partial phases of the eclipse safely through a piece of #14 welder's glass.</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
<p style="text-align: left;">With the crowds of chasers along the beach and in town, it looked as if we had picked a perfect spot to watch the Shadow of the Moon approaching us.</p>

<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/mex_jeepsite.jpg" alt="mex jeep" />

From our vantage point looking down on the town of La Paz, we wait for the show to begin.</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">When the shadow finally swept across us I couldn't believe my eyes. It got so dark all the street lights went on in the town below. Night!! But it wasn't night. It was the monstrous Moon's shadow fresh from a run across the open Pacific.  I watched as the monstrous Moon shadow cut through the sky heading straight for me at 3000 kilometers per hour.  The wind picked up and the temperature dropped. The sky was being cut in half! Through a piece of welder's glass I watched the perfectly black disc of the Moon cross the final inch of the face of the Sun reducing it to a single sliver of brilliance. The town of La Paz faded into silhouettes before my eyes as the Moon's veil of darkness swept up every living soul from west to east. Planets and stars appeared over my head in a sky that was now deeper and more magical than any twilight I had ever seen. I blinked, dropped my welder's glass, and looked up with my naked eye as the Moon finally hid the last burst of sunlight behind its jagged edge. With the Sun now totally hidden behind the dark side of the Moon, I took my first few breaths in the Moon's umbra - the alien world known as TOTALITY.</p>

I shook off the goose-bumps as best I could but the hair on the back of my neck was up to stay. With my naked eye I could see past the edge of the Moon to the surface of the Sun where brilliant pink and red explosions of gas were leaping up into space. These prominences looked as if a crimson jewel-box had tumbled open from behind the black limb of the Moon. And burning in every direction was the atmosphere of the sun -  long, thin, luminescent streamers of gas and magnetism that cut into space like swords for 3 million kilometers in every direction!!

It was sublime.  It was as if our little spot on Earth had fallen out of time. It was as if we had been arrested in a dome of dark blue sky so the universe could peer in at us with its one giant eye to see if we were paying attention.  All of a sudden I was in a relationship with the universe.  I had never seen or felt anything like it before.
<p style="text-align: left;">Six minutes and fifty seconds of totality marched across my face in an instant. I'm not sure if I breathed or not. When it was over, I was an eclipse chaser.</p>

<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/bajadiamond_still501.jpg" alt="mex diamond" />

"The Diamond Ring" effect marks the beginning of totality in Baja July 11, 1991. photo Andreas Gada.</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/bajamid_still501.jpg" alt="mex mid" />

Mid totality. photo Andreas Gada</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/baja_still501_01.jpg" alt="mex max" />

Corona! Glorious corona! photo Andreas Gada.</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/wendy_91corona2.jpg" alt="mex wendy" />

A composite of multiple negatives, this is an outstanding photo of the corona!
http://wendycarlos.com/eclipse.html</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">I didn't know it at the time because it was my first, but the shape of the corona on 11 July 1991 was the most exquisite. It has become the standard by which all other coronas have been judged. Absolutely magnificent! It's no wonder I haven't been quite the same since.</p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[My first trip into the Shadow of the Moon was the one that changed me forever! An eclipse chaser was born that day in Baja California Sur back in 1991.  ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>668</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>1991-08-11 00:00:27</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>1991-08-11 04:00:27</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>total-solar-eclipse-11-july-1991-mexico</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="tripreport"><![CDATA[Trip Report]]></category>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>_edit_last</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[5]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>post-thumb</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/mexico_logo2_01-166x200.jpg]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[604]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[883]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[590]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>_oembed_788a3a82be2fdd785d9c0e9e26fe22d3</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[{{unknown}}]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Brazil - 03 November 1994</title>
		<link>http://eclipseguy.com/tripreport/brazil-03-november-1994</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 1994 23:05:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[eclipseguy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://eclipseguy.com/?p=760</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">My 4th Solar Eclipse</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">My 2nd successful Total Eclipse</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">My second continent on the chase</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>

<blockquote><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/babes_du_jour_500.jpg" alt="brazil babes" />

I love Brazil.</blockquote>
I didn't know it at the time. I booked this expedition with a Brazilian friend of mine - he grew up in Sao Paulo - and he had offered to show me around the country and see his first total eclipse. I was foaming at the mouth to see another one - Mexico in 1991 was feeling very distant - and the two annular eclipses I had chased in the meantime didn't quench my thirst for exotic adventure or umbral glory. Brazil did both. Big time.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/desert_shoot1_500.jpg" alt="brazil desert shoot" />

Eclipseguy in action! And Vicki loves the dunes at much as I do.</blockquote>
In South America, Brazil takes up almost as much space as all the other 12 countries combined. It's massive. From the all-important Amazon rain forest, to the loud, over-populated sprawl of Sao Paulo, to the pristine dunes of coral sands that line the beaches on the northeast coast, Brazil is a microcosm of the entire planet. Brazil can give you anything. And as is the case with any country, there are two ways to go: as a tourist, or as a local. Travelling this rich land with my Brazilian friend, Dimas, I saw a part of this land very few visitors get to see.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/desert_oasis_500.jpg" alt="brazil oasis" />

Fortaleza: where the mountains meet the dunes on the Atlantic coast.</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->

To begin this eclipse adventure, we rendezvous with an old friend of Dimas' in Fortaleza, rent a dune buggy, and spend a week bounding through the hills of sand en route Canoa que Brada - a quaint village buried in the sand that is known for its young crowd and vibrant night life. Following the coastline for days along the beach, we stop at fishing villages and sleep in guest houses and make new friends at every turn. This part of Brazil is unique. The best fish lunches ever! And so much fun!
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/desert_shoot_500.jpg" alt="brazil photographer" />

South of Canoa que Brada. Never a cloud in the sky.</blockquote>
We arrive in Canoa and it is literally built on the sand. Townsfolk are mostly artists, musicians, small business owners or ex-patriots from the city who fell in love with this sleepy locale by the beach and never went home. Yes - we're talking party central!
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/sandy_cross_500.jpg" alt="brazil cross" />

The shifting sands of time bury the buried in Canoa.</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/theboys_carla_500.jpg" alt="brazil carlaboys" />

Our team in Canoa - Carla and the boys.</blockquote>
We met Carla in a restaurant on the way up from Fortaleza. She was giving us directions to Canoa when we asked to her to join us as our guide! People in Brazil are great! And when we got stuck in the sand, these two local kids came to the rescue. They knew how to handle that dune buggy better than any of us.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/carla_shadow_500.jpg" alt="brazil grave shadow" />

Carla helps me freeze a moment in time.</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->

With a serious hang over, we make our way to Sao Paulo - one the biggest cities in the world; like Manhattan times ten - and enjoy the good life for a week. I don't think I got any sleep the whole time I was there! And I am really starting to love the Brazilians we are meeting. If only I could speak Portuguese!
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/capricorn_500.jpg" alt="brazil capricorn" />

The Tropic of Capricorn runs between Sao Paulo and Rio de Janeiro.</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/varig_plane_500.jpg" alt="brazil varig" />

Dimas and I board a Varig Airlines flight from Sao Paulo to Iguacu Falls.</blockquote>
The eclipse path cut a swath through the south central part of South America, and numerous expeditions were staged to intercept the shadow in Chile near Putre. But for those of us observing from the Brazilian side, there was only one choice: Iguacu Falls; the meeting point between Brazil, Argentina and Paraguay.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/iguacu_falls_map.jpg" alt="brazil falls" />

<img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/foz_wide_500.jpg" alt="brazil foz" />

Iguacu Falls - among the most spectacular waterfalls in the Western Hemisphere.</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/dm_falls_500.jpg" alt="brazil dm foz" />

Sightseeing before the big day.</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/paraguay_poster_500.jpg" alt="brazil poster ur" />

Every country in the path calls the eclipse their own.</blockquote>
Dimas has friends in Iguacu Falls so it's easy to find our way around town. We attend pre-eclipse meetings being held by tour operators in hotels, and begin to narrow down the options for observing sites. The concern is that the moisture in the air from the falls will condense into localized clouds as the air cools with the coming of the Moon's shadow. A small soccer field just outside of town emerges as the best choice to avoid this fate.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/dirt_road_500.jpg" alt="brazil dirt road" />

The road to totality in Brazil.</blockquote>
We arrive at our chosen site only to find a group from the Toronto Centre of the RASC already set up! My local astronomy club! I had no idea they were in Brazil. We join the group, which includes additional chasers from Europe and around the world, and begin the nervous anticipation of totality. My second encounter with the Moon's shadow is nigh.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/rasc_banner_500.jpg" alt="brazil rasc" />

Surprize! You're at home!</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/chasers_group_500.jpg" alt="brazil chasers" />

Eclipse chasers waiting for the shadow of the Moon to arrive.</blockquote>
During the partial phases of an eclipse - the 90 minutes or so before and after totality - chasers love to experience the unique visual phenomena that only a crescent sun can produce.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/adler_500.jpg" alt="brazil adler" />

An eclipse chaser from the Adler Planetarium in Chicago holds up a pinhole camera of sorts - each round hold reproducing the partially eclipsed sun.</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/partialon_chest_500.jpg" alt="brazil chest" />

Eclipseguy gets eclipsed!</blockquote>
The media always makes a fuss when an eclipse comes to town. And although they usually can't get the facts straight, they do a great job of creating excitement and raising awareness of this incredible event.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/reporter_500.jpg" alt="brazil reporter" />

A reporter from Eyewitness News in Iguacu Falls live before totality.</blockquote>
After a few tense moments where it looked like we might have some clouds, the sky cleared. This was still only my second total eclipse and I wasn't yet burdening myself with multiple cameras and video. I got to sit back and enjoy it.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/brazil_totality_alt_500.jpg" alt="brazil totality" />

With Venus decorating the sky during totality, I see the corona for the second time in my life, 03 November 1994. 50mm lens.</blockquote>
What a glorious thing to do with a day. But all it did was leave me wanting more. My first eclipse in Mexico in 1991 was so long, so intense, so beautiful, I hadn't got nearly enough this time. But that unmistakable post-eclipse glow lasted well into the next day.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/thumbs_up_500.jpg" alt="brazil thumbsup" />

The Moon will meet the Sun again in India in 1995.</blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Brazil is one of the most fascinating countries in the world.  An unreal setting for my second Total Eclipse of the Sun.  ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>760</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>1994-12-05 19:05:37</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>1994-12-05 23:05:37</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>brazil-03-november-1994</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="tripreport"><![CDATA[Trip Report]]></category>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>_edit_last</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[5]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>post-thumb</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/brazil_trip_thumb.jpg]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[883]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[590]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>India - 24 October 1995</title>
		<link>http://eclipseguy.com/tripreport/india-24-october-1995</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 1995 00:21:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[eclipseguy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://eclipseguy.com/?p=768</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">My 5th Solar Eclipse</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">My 3rd successful Total Eclipse</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">My 3rd continent on the chase</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/taj_mahal.jpg" alt="india taj main" />

India changes your mind.</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">My expedition to India in 1995, which included Singapore, Malasia, and Bali in Indonesia, was one of those intense life-changing experiences. I returned home a different person. A person with a more complete picuture of the world and of humanity's journey on this planet. India has the power to change your mind. At once a visceral confrontation with reality and a subtle invitation to reflection, India is surely one of those countries that defines life on Earth. I loved it. But I'm not so sure how important it is that you like India - it's more that India forces you into a conversation with it. And that conversation is what the stuff of life is all about.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/india_mapcopy.jpg" alt="india map" /></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">After a few days in New Delhi getting used to the insane traffic and off-world odours that waft through the streets, I make my way to Agra, home of the Taj Mahal, and our starting point for the eclipse.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/street_scene.jpg" alt="india street" />

Just another day for the locals. For me, a thrilling encounter with the ancient.</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
<blockquote style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/marigolds.jpg" alt="india marigolds" />

Observing the rich marigold trade was a first for me.</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/art_wall.jpg" alt="india art wall" />

This is India.</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Arriving at the outskirts of the Taj, you have no indication of the glorious structure that waits beyond. The little stone ticket booth where you pay your admission could have easily been missed in the mayhem of the tiny streets surrounding this magnificent mausoleum. The first hint that you are about to experience something extraordinary comes on the walk up to the gateway that guards the entrance to the actual Taj grounds.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/taj_enter_1.jpg" alt="india enter taj" />

The great gateway to the Taj.</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/taj_enter.jpg" alt="india taj" /></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">The line-ups to get through the gateway are astronomical. Men and women enter separately, and everyone is searched for weapons, paint, etc. When you emerge on the other side, miraculously, it is there. The Taj Mahal. The most awe-inspiring structure I have ever seen in my life.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/taj_cu.jpg" alt="india taj cu" />

The Taj Mahal.</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">It is absolutely breathtaking. At the perimeter of the grounds, from where it first comes into view, you are still a good 400 metres from touching it and the sheer enormity sets it. I was baffled and silenced at once. The form and the majesty of the place to my eyes was enough, then the feeling set in. The spirit element beholding the Taj as I approached the centre mosque was as palpable as the visible wonder itself. I could not tear my eyes from it. It was actually magnetic. As I got closer and closer the impact became greater and greater. As I slipped off my sandals to walk upon the cool marble I became utterly convinced that I was in a fairy tale. Built by Emperor Shahjehan as an expression of his deep love for his wife, it actually took 20,000 workers over 22 years to complete.</p>

<!--nextpage-->
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/taj_crowd.jpg" alt="india taj collage1" /></p>

<img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/indian_woman.jpg" alt="india taj collage2" />
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/taj_detail_1.jpg" alt="india taj collage3" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/taj_detail_2.jpg" alt="india taj collage4" /></p>

You are invited to spend as much time as you like hanging out on the beautifully crafted terraces that surround the mosque where Shahjehan and his wife are buried. Knowing that it was built from love gives this place a very special energy. The Taj is a living thing. It interacts with you. The peace that emanates from its walls kept me there for hours and motivated several return visits.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/marble_trades.jpg" alt="india marble trades" />

Tiny street runs like arteries from the heart of the Taj, lined with artisans crafting marble
as they have for centuries.</blockquote>
Our eclipse observing site is Fatehpur Sikri. Located a few hours south of Agra, it was the political capital of India's Mughal Empire in the 16th century before it was abandoned due to a lack of water. Now it is an historic site with a beautiful central tomb and located directly in the eclipse path. Our driver, Marouf, arrives at 4am to take us there. For the next few hours, the fright and shock of rural India goes by out the window. Streets are unbelievable - peasants sleep in the gutter and roam about amongst the garbage and debris. Pedestrians, cyclists, motorcycles, cars of all sizes, buses, vans, massive trucks all jockey to be in front of the other guy. Opposing traffic lines mean nothing - you drive anywhere. We almost kill people regularly. And we see accidents every few miles. How India became one of the world's most populous countries doesn't seem to make any sense.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/busy_streets.jpg" alt="india busy street" /> <img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/busy_streets_1.jpg" alt="india busy street1" />

But we arrive in one piece - a little frayed and a little wiser.</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/sikri_grounds.jpg" alt="india sikri" />

Fatehpur Sikri is another encounter with the ancient spirit - ever present in India.</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
I was thrilled when I saw our location. We have nothing ancient and sacred like this in Canada. And even though these structures had been standing since the 16th century it was new to me, and I began to explore the site with a sense of excitement that only eclipse day can generate.

It was barely 6:30am and yet there were thousands of people here. Mostly local Indians, some tourists, and eclipse chasers from around the world. Everyone seemed to have the same unconventional, exotic look to them as if the mainstream was unaware this was happening at all and sent no delegates.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/sikri_wall.jpg" alt="india chasers gather" />

<img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/sikri_wall_1.jpg" alt="india chasers gather1" />

Thousands gather in the early morning mist anticipating nature's greatest spectacle.</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/goat.jpg" alt="india goat" />

Still a bit sleepy but right in the front row.</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/girl_shades.jpg" alt="india girl shades" />

8am. The partial phases are underway...</blockquote>
The massive red-stone stairway that leads to the gates of the temple are the obvious choice to observe from as they face directly towards the rising sun. I frequently refer to the NASA eclipse bulletin for technical information about the eclipse and suddenly find myself explaining what we're going to see to groups of people gathered around me. At an eclipse you tend to gravitate to anyone who seems to know more than you, and at this location that person was me! And although this is a job I am more than happy with, I wasn't prepared to be mauled by the local kids who would jump on me, grabbing, everytime I handed eclipse shades out to anyone. They wanted anything from me they could get their hands on. I actually had them hanging off me as I tried to move away. But with the eclipse now underway, I made my way back to the steps and watched as the light began to disappear.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/crescent_pants.jpg" alt="india crescent pants" />

Projecting out of the eyepiece of my binoculars it's easy to follow the partial phases without looking up.</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/seated_crowd.jpg" alt="india first timers" />

Mostly first-timers, these people have no idea what they are in for.</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/demas_looksup.jpg" alt="india dimas looks" />

This is the second encounter with totality for my friend Dimas.</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/couple_shades.jpg" alt="india couple waits" />

All ready for the Moon to do its thing.</blockquote>
In the seconds before totality, everyone was standing, and the noise and excitement was rising to a climax. I looked around for shadow bands but couldn't find any. I looked at the eclipse hoping to see a few Baily's Beads, but couldn't see any! The corona seemed to pop into view without any if its usual announcements! But there it was - totality - much to the delight and the shrieks of the gathered faithful. The shadow of the Moon had transformed our remote outpost in rural India into an alien world. The eclipse looked much bigger to me than my other two eclipses, probably because the sun was so low in the sky. Not even forty degrees. You only had to look over to see it, not up. And just as predicted, Jupiter and Venus were adorning this celestial wonder on either side. A true astronomical marvel! But then before I could exhale, it was over. The total eclipse had lasted 59 seconds. But it felt more like 2.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/totality.jpg" alt="india totality" />

Totality 24 October 1995 at Fatehpur Sikri, India. 50mm lens.</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/totality_birds.jpg" alt="india totality birds" />

The birds went crazy!</blockquote>
Most animals don't know what to make of totality. Mostly it upsets their day/night rhythm and they get spooked. We were delayed leaving this site because a cow had decided to sit down on the road during totality and refused to get up again!
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/temple.jpg" alt="india temple" />

The Tomb of Salim Chisti</blockquote>
With the incredible lift in spirit that comes with seeing a total eclipse, we spent the rest of the afternoon basking in the glorious feeling of being alive, and exploring this fascinating site. Eclipse days are always a peak experience, but even more so in an exotic locale. I never would have visited Fatehpur Sikri without the eclipse and I never would have felt the presence of Sheik Salim Chisti by standing in his tomb.

We travelled back to Delhi, on to Singapore, then drove around the island of Bali for a week. When I got home I began the long and nasty 3-year wait to see totality again.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[I was definitely not prepared for India!  But when my time there was over, I did not want to leave.  ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>768</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>1995-11-23 20:21:27</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>1995-11-24 00:21:27</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>india-24-october-1995</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="tripreport"><![CDATA[Trip Report]]></category>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>_edit_last</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[5]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>post-thumb</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/taj_cu-200x138.jpg]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[883]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[590]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>587</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Eclipseguy.com – Eclipse Chasing, Solar Eclipse Videos, Trip Reports, Galleries &raquo; 24 Years of Expeditions]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email></wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://eclipseguy.com/news/20-years-of-expeditions</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>76.9.192.81</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2015-03-24 16:12:33</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2015-03-24 20:12:33</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[[...] Oct 1995 &#8211; Fatehpur Sikri, India - Total -  [...]]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type>pingback</wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Zambia - 21 June 2001</title>
		<link>http://eclipseguy.com/tripreport/zambia-21-june-2001</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2001 02:07:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[eclipseguy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://eclipseguy.com/?p=785</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">My 10th Solar Eclipse</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">My 6th successful</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Total Eclipse in a row</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">My 5th continent on the chase
<img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/kidslookup1.jpg" alt="zambia kids look" />
<p style="text-align: left;">The best days of my life have been eclipse days. The rush of exotic travel - the unparalleled excitement of finally arriving in the eclipse zone - the gratification of sharing such a sublime natural event with the local families - and that post-eclipse glow that keeps me going well into the next day, and beyond. All this makes for some pretty remarkable memories. In fact, over the years, I have meditated on my eclipse experiences so frequently that I can recall the most exquisite of details even years later.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Much of the richness of the experience comes from the location you choose to observe the eclipse. Your immediate surroundings can add tremendously to the impact of the day if you choose carefully. I like to be somewhere that already has its share of magic - like a Hindu temple in India, an ancient archeological site in Turkey, or in the case of Africa, a school yard in rural Zambia full of local children.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">I usually end up on the chase by myself (it's hard to find people who can take these big trips!), but on this one I traveled with a group of mostly Canadian chasers organized by the Calgary Science Centre.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/wholegroup1.jpg" alt="zambia group" />

Friends celebrate the eclipse. That's me holding the Canada flag!</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">Along with seeing the eclipse we took the opportunity to explore a bit of central Africa. We flew into Harare, stayed a few nights in Lusaka to do some night sky observing, visited the famed Victoria Falls, and spent a week on safari in Malawi.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/overvicfalls1.jpg" alt="zambia vicfalls" />

My helicopter shot of the great rift that is Victoria Falls.</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/jeepbeauty1.jpg" alt="zambia jeep" />

On safari in eastern Zambia! These jeeps can go anywhere.</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/giraffes1.jpg" alt="zambia giraffes" />

I saw so many giraffes and elephants and rhinos and exotic birds I could never post all the pictures!</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
<p style="text-align: left;">Being on this safari was like being transported back into prehistory. In this part of Africa, time has stood still for centuries. And as a first time visitor I was amazed by the beauty of the habitat and the sense of the ancient in everything. Quite a tactile difference compared to my North American home environment of all new concrete and steel.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Each day we set out on to the land in our Jeeps at sunrise and at sunset. These are the times when the animals are moving around. With two cameras in a bag, a proper hat and a cold beer between my legs I was in heaven everyday as we bounced across fields and forest and streams hoping to sneak up on some big animals. And it happened daily.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">If you've never been on a safari I would recommend making plans now to get it done. Not to be missed!</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/dustrails1.jpg" alt="zambia dust trail" />

Dust trails at dusk. A night time safari begins.</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/roadtomalam1.jpg" alt="zambia road" />

Taking a stretch on the road to our eclipse site.</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">Eclipse day is always the best day! Like my chaser friend, Jeff Collinson, likes to put it, "...it's like Christmas morning!"</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Our observing site, the village of Malambanyama, was a four hour drive from Lusaka that started at 8am. The road looks good in the above picture - but that was the only good spot! The rest was only tolerable because I knew there was a pot of gold waiting for us at our destination. And indeed there was.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">One of the best things I have ever been involved with was the presentation of school supplies by our group in exchange for permission to observe the total eclipse from the school's playground. A poor, rural village, devastated earlier in the year by floods, the Head Master of the school was thrilled to make the arrangement. And they were right in the path of totality - perfect for us. The exercise books, dictionaries, pens and materials will last them ages - and the memories for all of us, a lifetime.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">The ceremonial presentation of our gifts is in my video Africa Total Eclipse. Get your copy!</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/daveshootkids1.jpg" alt="zambia shoots" />

eclipseguy gets video of the school children in song before the eclipse.</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">A fun thing to do when the partial eclipse has started is to play with projections of the image of the partially eclipsed sun. Projections can be thrown in all sorts of neat ways - with pieces of mirrored glass - with telescopes and binoculars - through bushes and trees and hats - and by punching pinholes in a piece of cardboard. The picture below was made from the lid off my box lunch! All the holes reveal little crescent suns!</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: left;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/pinhole1.jpg" alt="zambia pinholes" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Even the smallest pinholes reveal the sun in partial eclipse.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">Serious eclipse chasers usually fit into one of two categories. The ones who just want to be there when it happens - to drink-in the sublime beauty of totality - and the ones who are equally serious about taking pictures of it. With totality normally so fleeting you can't really do both. This is one of the chaser's inescapable realities. Sometimes a computer can work the camera for you while you watch the sky, but your full attention is still not on the eclipse. I had seen many eclipses without paying much attention to shooting them and I never regretted it. But this time - with totality almost 4 minutes long - I decided to try to do both!</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">In a playground somewhere in rural Africa I waited for the shadow to come with forty foreign and frantic eclipse chasers, with hundreds of pounds of telescopes, and a few dozen African kids who had never seen such a scene! What a day for all of us!</p>

<!--nextpage-->
<blockquote style="text-align: left;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/schnieder01.jpg" alt="zambia totality" /></p>

<p style="text-align: center;">A single "Baily's Bead" adorns the eerie blackness of the Moon's dark side just as totality begins.
Photo: Glenn Schneider</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: left;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/afeclipse.jpg" alt="zambia wide" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">My first good shot of an eclipse! Taken 21 June 2001 w/28mm lens.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">We could see the shadow coming at us from miles away. Totality hit right on time and the corona came into view. Spectacular! The chromosphere was intense this time and there was a neat, detached prominence that you can see in Glenn's shot above. The playground went wild! I spent the first minute yelling and screaming about how great it was, and framing up my video camera, then I let it go and sat down beside my Nikon to fire off a planned sequence of shots with a cable release. It was a lot to do in such a short time. When it was over, I had a few moments when I wished I hadn't spent so much time shooting! Every second truly is precious.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">The corona was tremendous. A nice, round, even set of streamers with intensely sharp, sword-like brushes.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: left;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Sirois2001_long2.jpg" alt="zambia corona" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The crowning glory of a total eclipse! photo Andre Sirois</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">The school yard had been turned into an alien planet. The sight of totality is unreal! You've got to see one of these things before you die!</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Check out the clips from my film Africa Total Eclipse in the Media Vault!</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Now I am very busy organizing the next total eclipse chase! See you there?</p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Africa is called the Dark Continent.  But with the light in the eyes of all the Zambians I met, and the spectacle of a Total Eclipse, I can't imagine why. ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>785</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2001-07-21 22:07:19</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2001-07-22 02:07:19</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>zambia-21-june-2001</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="tripreport"><![CDATA[Trip Report]]></category>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>_edit_last</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[5]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>post-thumb</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Sirois2001_long2-200x168.jpg]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[971]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[649]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[883]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[590]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>629</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Eclipseguy.com – Eclipse Chasing, Solar Eclipse Videos, Trip Reports, Galleries &raquo; 24 Years of Expeditions]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email></wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://eclipseguy.com/news/20-years-of-expeditions</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>76.9.192.81</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2015-04-12 11:03:41</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2015-04-12 15:03:41</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[[...] Jun 2001 &#8211; Lusaka, Zambia &#8211; Total &#8211; [...]]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type>pingback</wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Outback - 02 December 2002</title>
		<link>http://eclipseguy.com/tripreport/outback-02-december-2002</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2003 00:46:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[eclipseguy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://eclipseguy.com/?p=797</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/ausbanner.jpg" alt="thin shadow banner" />
My 12th Solar Eclipse -
<p style="text-align: center;">My 7th successful</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Total Eclipse in a row -</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">My 6th continent on the chase</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/ravepostcard.jpg" alt="rave postcard" /></p>

In the years prior to 2002, I never thought I was going to go on this chase. It was really far across the globe, totality was only going to be 30 seconds at best and I figured the chances of seeing the eclipse were minimal. I could opt to see the eclipse from Africa instead but I knew I was going to Zambia in 2001!

Then, in late December 2001, when most eclipse chasers were licking their wounds from having been clouded out in Costa Rica, I had a pre-Christmas dinner with a couple from Sydney, Australia. She was an old friend, he was a pilot. They offered to put me up and organize a private flight into the Outback to see this eclipse. I thought about it for 5 seconds and agreed to their terms!

Planning to execute this chase took the entire year. Even while I was in Puerto Vallarta chasing the  annular eclipse at sea  I had the Outback on my mind.

In mid-November, 2002, I flew to Sydney and spent a week getting to know the city. I had always wanted to visit Australia, and after the Olympics in 2000 the desire was even stronger.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/operahouse.jpg" alt="aus opera house" />

The Sydney Opera House</blockquote>
Then I flew up to tropical North Queensland - to Port Douglas - to visit the Great Barrier Reef and to take part in one of my favourite activities - snorkelling!! This is one of the most exciting and beautiful parts of the world.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/reef.jpg" alt="aus reef" />

Our catamaran docks at the station on the Agincourt Reef, 90 minutes out from the coast. This shot was taken during my helicopter flight over the Reef.</blockquote>
By 30 November I was back in Sydney preparing for the once-in-a-lifetime experience of flying into the Outback to camp on a dusty airstrip. Being a devoted eclipse chaser takes me to places I would otherwise never go in a million years.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/baron58.jpg" alt="aus our plane" />

eclipseguy poses with the trusty Baron 58 used to get into the path of the total eclipse.</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
Five adventurers left Sydney on 01 December and took a leisurely 3 days to get to the eclipse site - stopping everyday at a new Outback town to explore the local culture and get a sense of one of the most alluring and remote regions on this planet.

We visited the wineries and citrus groves of Griffith - spent the night in an underground cave attached to an opal mine in White Cliffs - and joined hundreds of other eclipse chasers with eclipse fever in Leigh Creek.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/inflight.jpg" alt="aus inflight" />

At 9,500 feet eclipseguy enjoys the ride with eclipse first-timer George Macarthur.</blockquote>
If the thought of hopscotching through the Outback in a small plane scares the hell out of you, then you wouldn't have enjoyed this trip! Personally, I can't get enough of this stuff. It seems that if I am chasing an eclipse, I am willing to do almost anything. Plus, I have way more fun than most people!
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/pathsign.jpg" alt="aus path sign" />

A great AP photo!</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/campsite.jpg" alt="aus campsite" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Our landing strip campsite in the giant "dust-bowl" know as Lyndhurst.</p>

Lyndhurst (population 25) was lucky enough to be situated directly in the path of the Total Eclipse and had one of the few serviceable landing strips we could use. We arrived the day before the eclipse with the intention of camping for two nights. During the forty hours we were, the stiff southerly wind never let up and it was a struggle to keep the tents from collapsing. Using the gas stove to prepare any hot food was out of the question. Fortunately for us, the eclipse had brought more visitors to Lyndhurst than it had ever seen in its history and there were truck-loads of food and water available at the Elsewhere Hotel, a tiny Outback watering hole two kilometres behind us!
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/hotel.jpg" alt="aus hotel" />

Elsewhere Hotel. Centre of the eclipse universe!</blockquote>
With the thousands of freaky revelers brought in by the well-organized Eclipse Outback Festival, Lyndhurst was a carnival of sights and sounds and celebration. This was a very different energy than my eclipse experiences in Turkey or India which were at sacred archeological sites. But I was loving the change. This was truly a giantic eclipse bash complete with 24 hour-a-day trance music, all the food and drink you could desire, and artists and dancers and crafts from 20 different countries!
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/ravecamp.jpg" alt="aus rave site" />

This is what a campsite for 6,000 looks like.</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/raventer.jpg" alt="aus rave enter" />

What's a festival without tons of banners and flags?
(Notice they are all tilted to the right in the wind)</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/ravestage.jpg" alt="aus rave stage" />

Dancin' in a dust-bowl.</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/selfportrait.jpg" alt="aus self port" />

(self-portrait) I'm pretty sure that I consumed about a cup of sand that day.</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/inthedust.jpg" alt="aus road dust" />

Less than an hour before the eclipse, hundreds of chasers line the road into Lyndhurst as a Festival transport truck kicks up the dust!</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
By the time the partial phase of the eclipse had started, more than a dozen small planes had joined us on the airstrip. And we had perfect weather! Blue skies everywhere! Only trouble was that wind. Securing my photo and video equipment took extra work. But it paid off.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/austotality1.jpg" alt="aus totality" />

Totality - 04 December 2002 - Lyndhurst airstrip</blockquote>
It was truly gorgeous from Lyndhurst! This was one of the prettiest totalities I have ever seen. It glimmered so much - like it had come tumbling out of a jewel box. I was breathless at how much chromosphere was visible right at second contact. I couldn't believe it. And the shape of the shadow cone! I'd never seen from inside the umbra at this angle before. It was wild to see it almost bending towards me. I was only just beginning to believe my eyes when the diamond ring burst out again and it was over! My shortest total eclipse ever - 24 seconds!
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/dmdring.jpg" alt="aus diamond" />

A beauty shot of the diamond ring! Photo: Klipsi</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/grin_outback02.jpg" alt="aus dm grin" /></p>

This amazing eclipse gave us the chance to see inside the umbra, the Moon's shadow, from a different angle. We were so close to the end of the entire eclipse path on the Earth that most of the cone-shaped umbra had already begun to lift off back into space. As a result, we were standing only in the part of the shadow that was still touching the ground.

When the eclipse was over we made our way back to the Elsewhere Hotel for their eclipse celebration BBQ and piss up! Watch where you're going in the dark! I am always in the mood to celebrate after a successful eclipse and so were the Aussies! The night-time skies in the Outback were the darkest I had ever seen and I spent hours observing all the wonderful sights of the southern sky including my first ever sightings of the Magellanic Clouds and The Southern Cross rising!

You don't know dark until you've camped in the Outback.

Thanks goes to the awesome Australian connection who helped me pull this off!
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/group.jpg" alt="aus group" />

George Macarthur - Ali Montgomery - Deb Taylor - Matt Montgomery</blockquote>
Now I am very busy organizing the next total eclipse chase! See you there??]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[This is one of the most extreme expeditions ever!  You have not lived until you have camped in the Outback! ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>797</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2003-01-10 20:46:34</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2003-01-11 00:46:34</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>outback-02-december-2002</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="tripreport"><![CDATA[Trip Report]]></category>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>_edit_last</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[5]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>post-thumb</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/pathsign-200x200.jpg]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[993]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[658]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[654]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[595]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[883]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[590]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Antarctica - 23 November 2003</title>
		<link>http://eclipseguy.com/tripreport/antarctica-23-november-2003</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2003 04:00:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[eclipseguy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://eclipseguy.com/?p=813</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">My 13th Solar Eclipse -</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">My 8th successful</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Total Eclipse in a row -</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">My 7th continent on the chase</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/the_explorer.jpg" alt="ant explorer" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/TSE2003map1.jpg" alt="ant map" />We made history! On this date, I was among the first humans to ever witness a total eclipse from Antarctica.</p>

Along with one hundred passengers from 15 countries I journeyed 8,000 miles aboard the Russian icebreaker Kapitan Khlebnikov from Port Elizabeth, South Africa to Hobart, Tasmania. The month-long expedition took us to the far side of Antarctica - a location few people have ever visited. And as far as I know, we were the only marine expedition in the world to attempt an observation from the eastern ice shelf.

During the three weeks we sailed south in the Indian Ocean, we landed at Crozet and Kerguelen Islands and visited with the thousands of King Penguins that colonize the sub-Antarctic islands. Arriving in the sea ice that surrounds the continent, we made our way east into the Davis Sea to try to find a spot in the path of totality.

Unpredictable ice and weather were our daily concerns. The thick, fast ice had already prevented us from making two of our intended landings on the continent, and the cold, wind and clouds were showing no signs of letting up.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/group_berg.jpg" alt="ant group fisheye" />

Eclipse chasers of the icebreaker Kapitan Khlebnikov explore the majestic landscapes of the Far Side.</blockquote>
Only six hours before the eclipse was to begin, the captain of the Khlebnikov found this shelf of sea ice and rammed the bow into its edge. Now safely "garaged" in the ice - and finally in the path of totality - we began the process of staking out the site.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/site_shelf.jpg" alt="ant ice shelf" width="504" height="139" />

<img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/big_berg.jpg" alt="ant berg" />

Within the hour, Expedition Staff had landing supplies on the ice. Eclipse chasers waited out the final few hours before the eclipse in the warmth of the ship before heading out to set up.</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/khleb1.jpg" alt="ant ship" />

Russian icebreaker Kapitan Khlebnikov "garaged" in the sea ice, west of the Shackleton Ice Shelf.</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/new_chasers.jpg" alt="ant penguins" />

Curious locals wonder what all the fuss is about.</blockquote>
Three hours before First Contact, groups of eclipse chasers begin setting up their equipment in anticipation of an event that has brought them to the bottom of the Earth and to the most unforgiving climate in the world.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/didier1.jpg" alt="ant didier" />

Didier Raboud from the University of Geneva aligns his equipment.</blockquote>
In many ways, this eclipse was unique and it drew the attention of chasers around the world. In Iran, where astronomy has been practiced for thousands of years, the amateur community is made up of only a handful of enthusiasts. Babak A. Tafreshi and Hamid Khodashenas are the most dedicated of them, and were the only Iranians in the path of totality. Throughout the expedition, they sent daily reports back to Iran in an effort to raise awareness of astronomy in their home country.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/babak.jpg" alt="ant babak" />

With all his equipment working in the freezing cold, Babak A. Tafreshi enjoys a moment during the pre-eclipse jitters.</blockquote>
The expedition was rich with learning and first-hand experiences in the Antarctic. Expedition specialists gave lectures on history, geography and ornithology, and thanks to astronomy advisors Fred Espenak from NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center, and John Parkinson from Sheffield Hallam University in England, passengers had the opportunity to learn from the world's best.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/fred_shoots.jpg" alt="ant fred" />

Eclipse veteran Fred Espenak is known for producing stunning eclipse images. This was Fred's 18th total eclipse.</blockquote>
Just before the eclipse began, I gave a live interview by Iridium satellite phone to Discovery Channel Canada for their live broadcast about the eclipse. Natasha Stillwell from 'Daily Planet' spoke to me about the conditions on the ice, our preparations for eclipse day, and about the people we had on board the ship. As the only Canadian eclipse chaser on the expedition, it was a real thrill to speak to my country about what we were experiencing.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/discovery_phone1.jpg" alt="ant discovery" />

eclipseguy's 4am phone call with Discovery Channel from the bow of the Khlebnikov!</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
As you can see from the photo below, the clear skies we had enjoyed during set up quickly became threatened by a band of low, broken clouds from the north.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/wide1.jpg" alt="ant wide" />

What you don't want to see - clouds drifting in across the sun.</blockquote>
The only possible benefit of clouds during an eclipse is that they act as a solar filter of sorts, here making it easier to observe and photograph the partial phases. But if they stay around too long they might eclipse the eclipse itself.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/partial1.jpg" alt="ant partial" />

The eclipse chaser's nightmare - ghostly clouds making an appearance once the show has begun.</blockquote>
This frame-grab from video shows what we saw through the clouds as Second Contact arrived. Not a complete cloud-out, but not as clear as we had hoped. If it wasn't for the lucky placement of this small patch of transparent cloud we might have even seen less!
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/beads2.jpg" alt="ant beads" />

A few Baily's Beads expire as totality begins beyond the clouds.</blockquote>
As mid-totality arrives the clouds have decided to stay diminishing our view of the corona. Unfortunately, these meager shots don't do the experience justice. Yes - it was partly cloudy. But the real show wasn't in the sky this time. It was all around us. The colour of the sky during totality was stunning, and the amazing pastel hues cast upon the valley of icebergs was something I had never seen before. And it was very dark. I don't think I have ever seen the shadow move so quickly before.

I had always thought that an eclipse was about the corona - but this eclipse taught me that this isn't necessarily the case.

I have more pictures and video to post later that show the amazing colours the umbra cast upon our temporary home in the ice.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/mid_totality1.jpg" alt="ant midtotality" />

Enough to bring tears to your eyes. This was the most of the corona we observed during the fleeting 1 minute and 14 seconds we observed.</blockquote>
Below is my best shot of totality with my 28mm lens. Look closely and you will see the totally eclipsed sun near the centre of the frame!
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/totality_antarctica1c.jpg" alt="ant totality" />

Totality on 23 November 2003 from east of the Shackleton Ice Shelf in Antarctica.</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
It is truly amazing how different cameras can capture different views of the same event. In this angle to the west, Loren Dolman has frozen totality in time. This is exactly what was visible to the naked eye.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/solar_landscape1.jpg" alt="ant landscape" />

Loren Dolman's great shot of what this eclipse was about for us - being in the umbra.</blockquote>
The shadow races off across continental Antarctica - to a rendezvous with chasers at Novo Station.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/shadow_leaves.jpg" alt="ant shadow leaves" />

In this Luigi Boschin shot, the movement of the shadow across the tops of the clouds is striking.</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/explorer_2.jpg" alt="ant explorer2" /></p>

Thanks to Luigi Boschin, Loren Dolman, Rob Arnott and Peter Gronvall for sharing their images!

Now I am busy organizing the next total eclipse chase. See you there??!!]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Spending one month on a Russian icebreaker is an experience you don't soon forget. This was mankind's first glimpse of a Total Eclipse from the ice continent. ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>813</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2003-12-23 00:00:19</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2003-12-23 04:00:19</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>antarctica-23-november-2003</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="tripreport"><![CDATA[Trip Report]]></category>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>_edit_last</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[5]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>post-thumb</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/the_explorer-200x150.jpg]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[987]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[618]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[1074]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[590]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[883]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Libya - 29 March 2006</title>
		<link>http://eclipseguy.com/tripreport/libya-29-march-2006</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2006 15:54:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[eclipseguy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://eclipseguy.com/?p=834</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">My 14th Solar Eclipse</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">My 9th successful</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Total Eclipse in a row</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/sahara_oasis1a_500.jpg" alt="lib dm oasis" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/libya_poster_500.jpg" alt="lib poster" /></p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R205425A_500.jpg" alt="lib desert sand" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The Sahara Desert ...</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R1204219Acopy_500.jpg" alt="lib theatre" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The Roman Ruins outside of Tripoli ...</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R110219copy_500.jpg" alt="lib venice" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">with Venice, Italy ...</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R702812Acopy_500.jpg" alt="lib sicily" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">and the tiny island of Sicily thrown in as side trips ...</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">This was the eclipse adventure of a lifetime...</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/groupshot_500.jpg" alt="lib group" width="566" height="226" />
<p style="text-align: center;">The team that made it happen! Trekking in the desert with our Libyan guides! photo Andreas Gada</p>

<!--nextpage--></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">My life-long passion for chasing eclipses continued in March 2006 with a major expedition to the scorched landscapes of the Sahara Desert in Libya. One of the most intensely anticipated eclipses of my career, this trip deliverd more beauty, more adventure and more satisfaction than I could have possibly imagined. And I am very demanding! But the Libyans came through! Their country is a vast, seemingly timeless expanse that exerts an undeniable force - pulling on you from the inside. From this one, we all came back changed. It was like going to the Moon and back. Libya is without question one of the hidden gems of the world - The Sahara, one of the most mysterious places. To collide, here, with nature's grandest spectacle was one of the peak experiences of my life. So killer!</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">I embark on this journey with my friend Michael Riley. It's our second chase together. We leave home for almost a month on 17 March 2006 - full of hope and expectations. But we have no idea what is waiting for us on the other side of the world.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R1305023Acopy_500.jpg" alt="lib venice tower" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">We begin in Venice, Italy!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">I like to do a lot of travelling before the eclipse. The momentum of all the anticipation is great fuel. And I have to say that the beauty of a city built on water and the sheer novelty of the intricate canal system makes Venice one of the must-see cities of the world. A delight for a few nights...
<img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R110156_500.jpg" alt="lib venice water" />
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R1304822Acopy_500.jpg" alt="lib venice wall" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">There's nowhere like Venice.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R110114_500.jpg" alt="lib espresso" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Mmmm. Michael's two favourite things... espresso and red wine.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Our plan is to fill up on red wine &amp; Italian food before the prohibition and desert rations of Libya. So that's exactly what we do. I like!</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R70187A_500.jpg" alt="lib sicily building" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Palermo is our home base as we discover Sicily next.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R303415A_500.jpg" alt="lib agrigento" /> h</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The Valley of Temples at Agrigento on Sicily's south shores.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Within a few short hours from Palermo, you can be at any of Sicily's great sites. The island is a lush green rock surrounded by Mediterranean Sea - home to a rich traditional culture that remains untouched by the march of time.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R302611A_500.jpg" alt="lib mosiac" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The intricate mosaics of Piazza Armerina - 2nd century ruins in the heart of the island.</p>

<!--nextpage--></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">After a week travelling through Italy, we connect through Rome and before we know it we are walking the streets of Tripoli and exploring the last undiscovered stretch of Mediterranean coastline. Tripoli is a wonderfully peaceful and authentic Muslim city virtually untouched by tourism. There are no western businesses, no street advertising, no hustlers, no pressure. Any merchant, taxi driver or man on the street will lend a hand or a warm smile. It is easy and safe to get around. All my fears about my security and my preconceptions about this 'rogue terrorist dictatorship' turn out to be completely false.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R704822A_500.jpg" alt="lib market" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">El Madina - The Old City market in Tripoli. No tourist trap! This is where the Libyans shop!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">At once an ancient settlement conquered by empires and a thriving new metropolis vying for recognition by the west, Tripoli is a city of contrasts. Morning prayers ring out from the minarets at 6am and fill the air between the new hotels and old houses. Nothing if not a spiritual place, Tripoli showed me how peaceful and inspirational the dedication to Islamic prayer can be.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R707033A_500.jpg" alt="lib modern" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The future meets the past in downtown Tripoli.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/gaddafi_500.jpg" alt="lib ghaddafi" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Posters and billboards of leader Muammar Gaddafi are common all around Libya. He named the country The Great Socialist People's Libyan Arab Jamahiriya. photo Brendan Seaton</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">A short drive along the coast in either direction from Tripoli puts you at some of the best-preserved Roman ruins in the Mediterranean. I was never a huge fan of Roman ruins - until this...</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R90145Acopy_500.jpg" alt="lib archway" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The gates of Lepits Magna - a complete Roman city.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R903415Acopy_500.jpg" alt="lib arches" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">We are free to move about the site and experience it in intimate detail.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R120229Acopy_500.jpg" alt="lib stone wall" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Sabratha was the city by the sea.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R1203013Acopy_500.jpg" alt="lib statue" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R1204621Acopy_500.jpg" alt="lib theatre seats" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">If you listen closely you can still hear the sound of applause in the theatre.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R903817A_500.jpg" alt="lib stadium" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Guess how many it seats...</p>

<!--nextpage--></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Our expedition numbers over a hundred chasers from South Africa, Europe and North America. We spend the week re-acquainting with old friends, welcoming new ones, and trading stories of past chases. But we can't stay put for long. The Moon clocks our schedule with precision, and soon we must pack our crates full of telescopes and cameras and make our way out of Tripoli. At this point, I've got a bad case of eclipse jitters and my stomach is in knots from the excitement that only adventure travel can generate - but I'm feeling good. I'm on a collision course with the solar system and there is less than 24 hours to go!</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/TSE2006globecopy.jpg" alt="lib map globe" />
X marks the spot. The centre line of the eclipse - Sahara Desert, south of the Jalu Oasis.
<p style="text-align: center;">image courtesy Fred Espenak NASA/GSFC</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">We fly Libyan Arab Airlines to the little airstrip outside of Jalu. Never fly Libyan Arab Airlines! (They are constantly off schedule and we had a few really hard landings). The desert air is hot and dry and the terrain is as flat as a sheet of paper. From simply breathing I have tiny particles of sand and dust gritting between my teeth - something I discover I'll have to get used to. We drive along the barren highway towards our eclipse site and turn off onto a new road created just to bring chasers to the centre of the eclipse path. Within minutes, like a mirage appearing out of the shimmering heat, The Tent City comes into view. It is a temporary home for 4,000 eclipse chasers built by the Libyan government. But in all its years the Sahara has never seen this ...</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R60166Acopy_500.jpg" alt="lib umbra av" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Umbra Avenue!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R60145Acopy_500.jpg" alt="lib tents" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">One of two massive dining tents where chasers share meals.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">I can't even describe the rush of excitement I felt as we descended on our home in the desert. It was surreal. I felt as if I had just stepped into a scene from "Close Encounters" - all the believers gathered in the desert because we've been told something extra-terrestrial is going to happen. And this is exactly what it was.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">We move into our tents and spend the afternoon playing in the world's biggest sandbox. Who knew I'd be playing frisbee in the Sahara! After dinner we turn our attention to the skies. The sunset seems supernatural out here. When the stars arrive and Jupiter comes tumbling out of its celestial jewelbox we are treated to a night of Arabian wonders.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">But my adrenalin rush just won't subside. Everytime I turn my head, I see something I've never seen before. This is one of the most fantastic places I have ever been. I can't sleep - the eclipse is only hours away - and our Libyan hosts have pulled out all the stops and transformed the desert. I spend the night checking out the air-conditioned internet tent, crafts, live musicians, sound stages, fireworks, espresso bars and coolers full of non-alcoholic beer! Desert living is blowing my mind!</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R60208Acopy_500.jpg" alt="lib fred" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Fred Espenak is up early on eclipse day.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R60082Acopy_500.jpg" alt="lib peter " /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">South African chaser Peter Tiedt makes sure everything is where it's supposed to be!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">While everyone is marking their plots of sand and getting their equipment set up, Michael and I go off into a sea of rabid chasers from all over the world to get some video. We return to our observing site and get ready for what we all feel is going to be the eclipse of a lifetime.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R60229Acopy_500.jpg" alt="lib michael looks" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The eclipse has begun! We are on a collision course with totality that can't be stopped!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R602410Acopy_500.jpg" alt="lib andreas" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Veteran Canadian eclipse photographer Andreas Gada created a special mount for this eclipse, and customized all his computer gear to operate in the desert.</p>

<!--nextpage--></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">As the light dimmed and the wind picked up with the approach of the Moon's shadow, a chill ran up the back of my neck and left goosebumps all over my skin. I had travelled thousands of miles to be here and now the eclipse was only seconds away. The conditions were ideal. Venus was blazing in the sky and I could see the darkening on the horizon. When the umbra was only a few miles away the sun was but a sliver over my head, and with a stream of Shadow Bands racing across my feet, I looked up. The sky was black in front of me and the orange glow on the horizon - the sign of the umbra - looked like it was burning the sand from above. The surreal other-world of totality had come to us in the desert.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R605425A_rev1copy_500.jpg" alt="lib my totality" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">TOTALITY with my 300mm lens!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/prominences2_new_650.jpg" alt="lib prominence" />
<img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/prominences3_new_650.jpg" alt="lib prominence3" />
<p style="text-align: center;">Brendan Seaton gets these great shots of the chromosphere during totality ...</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/diamond_ring_500.jpg" alt="lib diamond" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">... and the Diamond Ring at 3rd contact! GLORIOUS!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">The cheers and cries echo across the dark desert floor as the eclipse bathes us in its unearthly light. Totality lasts 4 minutes and 4 seconds. Forever! I had enough time to take some photos, adjust my video cameras and just gaze, aghast, at how beautiful it was. I adored the corona at this eclipse. It was irregular and asymmetrical - my favourite kind of corona. The sky was really dark and hung over us as if Merlin's cape had just dropped out of the sky. Venus was brilliant - Mercury was obvious - stars were visible - the orange glow of the umbral rim was unbroken for 360 degrees of perfectly flat horizon, something I have never seen before - and a real treat, the ever-elusive Shadow Bands were easily visible on the sand just before and just after totality. Everybody saw them.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">After years of chasing I can tell you this was one of sweetest eclipses ever. Everything came together with a degree of ease and perfection that just made the experience that much more intense. Jalu was one of the most awesome places I have ever been - the conditions on eclipse day were perfect - and not a single detail fell out of place. We bet everything that the universe would turn out the way we hoped - and it did!</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">But when the eclipse was over, the real adventure into the Libyan Sahara was just beginning. Michael and I joined a much smaller group of adventurers heading deep into the southwestern Fezzan region. From Jalu we flew back to Tripoli and on to Sebha where we began a week of trekking in 4x4s and camping in the desert.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R106531copy_500.jpg" alt="lib 4x4" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">It's not the years, honey, it's the mileage. Still our trusty 4x4s!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Our plan is to drive west from Sebha - through the surreal landscapes of the Sahara - to Ghat, a small Libyan village at the border with Algeria.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Campgroundmountains_500.jpg" alt="lib wide camp" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The world's most breathtaking camp site. photo Brendan Seaton</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/moon_halo_500.jpg" alt="lib moon halo" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Just imagine doing this... night after night. photo Graham Vosloo</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R1004822A_500.jpg" alt="lib camp " /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Another silent morning dawns on our intrepid team.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Day after day we encounter sights that boggle the mind and stretch the imagination. Waking each day in the beauty and utter silence of the desert becomes one of my favourite things. It's not hard to see how easily this place gets under your skin.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R804822Acopy_500.jpg" alt="lib solo tent" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Never Cold. Always comfortable.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R1006229A_500.jpg" alt="lib blue mats" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R205827A_rev1copy_500.jpg" alt="lib guides" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Our Tuareg guides: hardened desert men who know their stuff.</p>

<!--nextpage--></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Within a few short days I have completely adapted to the reality here. No toilets, no showers, basic food, and only bottled water to drink - hot on the tongue from being stored in the Jeeps. But still I love every minute of it. I spend each day in a state of amazement. The beauty of the earth seems to carry me far. Rock formations, mountains and canyons live in between sweet soft dunes of copper and gold. Every moment here lost in time.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R104521_500.jpg" alt="lib mountains" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Alone in The Acacus Mountains.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R103918_500.jpg" alt="lib rock arch" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Yes. This is real.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R102913_500.jpg" alt="lib streaky sky" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Ancient tribes left rock carvings and paintings throughout southwestern Fezzan.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R10093_500.jpg" alt="lib cave art" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Depicting an era when North Africa was a lush landscape of rivers and wildlife.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R507033A_500.jpg" alt="lib sand1" /></p>

<p style="text-align: justify;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R100208A_500.jpg" alt="lib sand2" />
For some reason, Libya was an especially meaningful experience. I'm still digesting it so I am not sure exactly why I feel this way. But Libya did prove to me that everything I am doing to venture out into the world is right. All the thinking, the planning, the money, the time  -  I was richly rewarded for all of it. Never have I felt more in my element, more sure of myself or more justified in doing these crazy things that I do. The universe wants me to be out here. What a wonderful thing to think.
<p style="text-align: justify;">This expedition lifted the veil on a brand new part of the world, and in the process, revealed a brand new part of myself. One I am only just getting to know.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/R804621A_500.jpg" alt="lib red feet" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Do I still have to convince you to come with me next time?</p>
</blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[It is difficult to pick favourite trips - but Libya is a highlight of my eclipse chasing career.  Perfect from start to finish.  Don't miss this one! ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>834</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2006-04-15 11:54:06</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2006-04-15 15:54:06</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>libya-29-march-2006</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="tripreport"><![CDATA[Trip Report]]></category>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>_edit_last</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[5]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>post-thumb</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/libya_trip_thumb.jpg]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[981]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[978]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[975]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[1009]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[883]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[590]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>The Arctic - 31 July 2000</title>
		<link>http://eclipseguy.com/tripreport/the-arctic-31-july-2000</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2000 16:41:58 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[eclipseguy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://eclipseguy.com/?p=847</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">My 8th Solar Eclipse -</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">My First Partial Eclipse -</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">My First continent on the chase</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/legsonshore1.jpg" alt="arc legs" /></p>

I am lucky to have a friend who runs polar expeditions. In the spring of 2000 when we realized that one of his Russian ships, the Luybov Orlova, would be full of passengers in the path of a partial eclipse while on an expedition through the Northwest Passage, he offered me a position as one of the ship's lecturers and added the event to the itinerary.

We flew from Ottawa, the capital of Canada, to Iqaluit, the capital of our new province of Nunavut in the north. We boarded the Orlova in Sondre Stromfjord on the western coast of Greenland. From here we followed the Northwest Passage up the coast, visiting Inuit villages for a week. Then we crossed Baffin Bay and anchored at the tiny Arctic community of Pond Inlet.
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arcticmap4.gif" alt="arc map" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">We saw the eclipse from the little bay next to Pond Inlet called Eclipse Sound !</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">(map copyright 2002 Athropolis Productions Ltd.)</p>
</blockquote>
This was my first experience with ice bergs and I instantly fell in love with them. Their sleepy majesty offered all the Arctic character I could hope for and were the source of hours of amazement on deck.
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/giantberg1.jpg" alt="arc berg" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Sailing up the western coast of Greenland.</p>
</blockquote>
The landscape above the tree line is barren and beautiful. It's amazing to think that after millions of years creatures still survive and thrive here. We spotted polar bears, whales, seals and thousands of birds as we sailed the frigid Arctic seas.
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/iceflow1.jpg" alt="arc flow" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Cruising through the brash ice near Devon Island.</p>
</blockquote>
While you can't properly make them out in this picture of Prince Leopold Island below, this fascinating and lonely island is home to tens of thousands of birds. They were quite a sight to see as we motored along the coast in our zodiacs.
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/pr_leopold1.jpg" alt="arc leopold" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Prince Leopold Island - like something out of "Lord Of The Rings!"</p>

<!--nextpage--></blockquote>
On board the Orlova our experts taught us about the race to find the Northwest Passage in the mid-19th century. At Beechy Island we came across the grave sites of John Torrington and others from the Franklin expedition, and we explored the remains of Northumberland House - still strewn with the rusty, lead-contaminated food cans that killed the entire crew, including Sir John Franklin in 1847.
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/torrington1.jpg" alt="arc torrington" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The grave site of John Torrington. A haunting reminder of trailblazers who have come before us.</p>
</blockquote>
When you visit the Arctic in the northern hemisphere summer you get to experience the midnight sun. It never gets dark! Each night at 1am or 2am I had to force myself to bed because all of the normal rhythms of day and night were gone.
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/superboat1.jpg" alt="arc ship" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Our ship Luybov Orlova at midnight in the Arctic.</p>
</blockquote>
On the day of the eclipse, I had all the passengers come out on deck for the event. For many it was their first eclipse ever.
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/anderson1.jpg" alt="arc anderson" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Carl Anderson observes the partial eclipse from Eclipse Sound at the extreme north of Baffin Island.</p>
</blockquote>
This frame-grab from video shows the partial eclipse at its maximum from our location. I wasn't very organized in my photography for this eclipse, and this image was taken with a piece of welder's glass held up against the lens of a Video8 camcorder! Hey - it's better than nothing.
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/greensun2.jpg" alt="arc green" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The partial solar eclipse of 31 July 2000.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/legsonshore1.jpg" alt="arc legs" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Wanna come on an eclipse chase? Find out where we are going next.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[My first partial eclipse!  And my first time in the polar regions of our Earth.  Outstanding adventure back into the ice age.  ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>847</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2000-08-31 12:41:58</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2000-08-31 16:41:58</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>the-arctic-31-july-2000</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="tripreport"><![CDATA[Trip Report]]></category>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>_edit_last</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[5]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>post-thumb</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/legsonshore1-200x130.jpg]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[883]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[590]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Puerto Vallarta - 10 June 2002</title>
		<link>http://eclipseguy.com/tripreport/puerto-vallarta-10-june-2002</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2002 17:36:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[eclipseguy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://eclipseguy.com/?p=872</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[In June 2002, I joined eclipse chasers from around the world in Puerto Vallarta, Mexico, to observe a spectacular annular eclipse at sunset. Many of us had never met before - acquainted only by the internet. Still, hundreds of us descended on this sleepy resort town on the Pacific coast of Mexico for a few days to witness a once-in-a-lifetime event.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/p_hotel_01.jpg" alt="puerto hotel" />

Puerto Vallarta, Mexico</blockquote>
Choosing an exact observing site for any eclipse is serious business. Each time there are different factors to consider in time and space and weather in order maximize your chances of actually seeing the thing. One little cloud can add the perfect touch or erase the sun altogether. And you never know which it is going to be until you're there.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/danielfisher.jpg" alt="puerto daniel" />

Eclipse chaser Daniel Fisher from Germany considers his options for an observation at sea.</blockquote>
In the days prior to the eclipse, I teamed up with chasers Olivier "Klipsi" Staiger from Switzerland, and Daniel Fisher from Germany. We soon discovered that a tropical storm was brewing off the coast - right in our backyard. Satellite images confirmed that tropical storm Boris was staying put for eclipse day. Arghhh!
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/storm.jpg" alt="puerto storm" />

Satellite image of tropical storm Boris</blockquote>
This was the worst possible development! Thick clouds, wind and rain are a nightmare come true!

Nevertheless, observing sites were chosen and cameras, lenses and telescopes were packed. A hundred of some of the busiest eclipse chasers in the world, many of whom had never met before, gathered at the Hard Rock Cafe the night before to share our concerns about Boris and trade whatever secrets we had discovered. You might think that we see each other over and over again at eclipses. Sometimes we do. But with so many of us scattered around the world, and so many different locations to observe from along eclipse paths, mass gatherings of top chasers are relatively rare. It was a real pleasure to finally meet people I had known about for years.

The next day we set out in a race, in dozens of splintered expeditions, to seek the Moon's anti-umbra.

While many chose to drive into the path of the eclipse 50 kilometers south of Puerto Vallarta, I chose to go by sea. I had never seen an eclipse on the ocean and this was my chance to do it.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/serape.jpg" alt="puerto serape" />

We set out on the M.S. Sarape from Marina Terminal, Puerto Vallarta</blockquote>
I joined 150 passengers, including Jay Pasachoff, the chair of the International Astronomical Union's Working Group on Eclipses, on the MS Serape bound for the waters off Cabo Corrientes. With tropical storm Boris still waving its ugly hand in the air, I believe we were the only organized team to attempt an observation by sea. For some it was well worth it. For others, a nightmare.

Our poor vessel had never seen such stormy seas. During our harrowing three hour journey inside the northern limit of the eclipse path, over half of our passengers became extremely sea sick, retching and vomiting beyond capacity. Then the gift shop exploded - the incessant pitching and keeling of the boat becoming too intense. The glass display cases and stands snapped into shards sending souvenirs flying as we buckled under the pressure of the waves. To make things even worse, there was water crashing in the windows on the lower deck every time we hit hard. And we weren't even there yet.

Still, the mayhem didn't stop Jay Pasachoff from presenting a great slide show about what we were hoping to see when we arrived. And I thought I had seen it all!

By the time we entered the zone of annularity, people were so sick it was only the most keen of us paying any attention to what was happening. Great beds of clouds ruled the skies with only scattered breaks where the Sun was supposed to be. I was sure we would see partial phases in part but I was wrong. Holding on for dear life and juggling a 300ml lens (which was futile) we got our only treat of the trip. A brilliant tangerine diamond burst out of the clouds - growing like a diamond ring at third contact. Then another! It was both sides of annularity! Through a break in the clouds less than a quarter of a degree wide we observed the nine and three o'clock positions of the ring for a few seconds. Prayers went skyward for a reappearance on the horizon - but it was not meant to be. I know both Jay and I tried our best to record the event, but it was Daniel Fisher that got the best results with his video camera. The rest of us were just lucky to be alive.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/stormsky.jpg" alt="puerto clouds" />

The annular eclipse as seen through the clouds of tropical storm Boris. Photo Glenn Schneider</blockquote>
But we all agreed that we had set a new standard in qualifying for a successful eclipse chase - the shortest observation ever!

The return journey was less rough and extremely subdued but I still had that post-eclipse glow. We dragged our soggy bottoms back into port about 11:30pm.

I consider the chase to be a complete success and one of the most outrageous of my career. I loved it! But there are many who would beg to differ and many who would do it all again.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[I have no luck with Annular Eclipses!  This was my second annular wash-out. ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>872</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2002-07-15 13:36:28</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2002-07-15 17:36:28</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>puerto-vallarta-10-june-2002</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="tripreport"><![CDATA[Trip Report]]></category>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>_edit_last</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[5]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>post-thumb</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/vallarta_trip_thumb.jpg]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[883]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[590]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>China - 01 August 2008</title>
		<link>http://eclipseguy.com/tripreport/china-01-august-2008</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2008 13:15:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[eclipseguy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://eclipseguy.com/?p=929</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0725.jpg" alt="chi me tarmack" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">My 15th Solar Eclipse</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">My 10th successful Total Eclipse in a Row</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">China is one of the most ancient civilizations in the world.  China's countless inventions, medicines and its contributions to human knowledge have made it a force on this planet for thousands of years. And the Chinese have been great astronomers, too.  Their prehistoric records of solar eclipses have provided critical information to historians.  And with two TSEs in two years and the Olympics in 2008, it seems there has never been more focus on China.</p>
<p style="text-align: right;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0156.jpg" alt="chi cool street" /></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">In today's world, China is still a force to be reckoned with.  It is the most populous country in the world  - has one of the fastest-growing economies and is central to world trade.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0160.jpg" alt="chi needle tower" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Downtown Shanghai</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Across its nearly 10 million square kilometers of land, it seems to offer adventure travellers everything they could want from rugged mountain ranges to subtropical forests to unforgiving desert.  And the ultra-modern cities like Beijing or Shanghai pulsate with commerce, culinary delights, and sights to astound even the most experienced traveller.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0856.jpg" alt="chi high city view" /> <img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0861.jpg" alt="chi high city street" /></p>
<p style="text-align: right;"><!--nextpage--></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">But  I never wanted to go to China.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Its ancient history and visual marvels notwithstanding, China has always been at the bottom of my list of places to go.  The allure of this fascinating civilization never reached me, and if it wasn't for the Total Eclipse of the Sun of 01 August 2008 - best observed from northwest China near the Mongolian border -  it would still be at the bottom of my list.</p>
<p style="text-align: right;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0240.jpg" alt="chi pagoda" /></p>
<p style="text-align: right;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0244.jpg" alt="chi pagoda detail" /></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">But this is one of the great things about being an eclipse chaser.  It takes me to places I would never go in a million years.  And in as much as the eclipses force me to choose destinations I wouldn't otherwise choose, they teach me about the world - broaden the boundaries of my life - by taking me outside of my comfort zone.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">And now that I have been to China and come back, I can say that I am really glad I went, if for no other reason than to experience the worst eclipse day of my life.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">My fifteen hour flight from Toronto ends in Shanghai.  I join an eclipse expedition as the staff photographer.  Taking pictures is something I love and it is great to have my photography pay my way on these trips!</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Our journey to totality begins when we fly to Urumqi in the country's far northwest.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0248.jpg" alt="chi urumqi" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Urumqi. The start of the ancient Silk Road.  I was expecting little villages!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">We are now in Xinjiang, part of China's Uyghur Autonomous Region.  Here, the Uyghurs - an ethnic Muslim minority - make up most of the population, whereas it is the Han Chinese that make up over 90% of China's 1.3 billion people.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0301.jpg" alt="chi dolkun" />
Our excellent Uyghur guide Dolkun!</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Driving along the Silk Road, we arrive at Turpan - the hottest, driest place in China.  And, at 500 feet below sea level, it is the second lowest place on Earth.  A cute little town of a few hundred thousand, Turpan is mostly about grapes and raisins.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0420.jpg" alt="chi grape canopy" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">A canopy of hanging grape vines in Turpan.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0516.jpg" alt="chi grape close" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">What it's all about in Turpan!</p>

<!--nextpage--></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Some of the big boulevards and promenades and little shops are very quaint.  Donkey carts, watermelon stands, scooters, open-air markets, animals  - the kind of village character that reminds me of Turkey or even Libya.  Must be the Muslim sensibility.  I walk around for a few hours on my own taking these pictures.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0518.jpg" alt="chi raisin stacks" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The final product.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0523.jpg" alt="chi raisin lady" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Cheap and delicious!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Nestled beneath snow-capped peaks is Heavenly Lake - an easy day-trip from Urumqi.  Mostly a vacation spot for locals, we saw one couple getting married here.  The culture of the Uyghurs is very different from most Chinese.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0308_01.jpg" alt="chi heav lake" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Heavenly Lake.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0311.jpg" alt="chi heav boat" /></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Across the lake, we arrive at a Toaist Temple - hike up the mountain - and take a few hours to look around.  I love temples and religious sites.  They are always the most memorable and deeply-felt of the places I shoot.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0322.jpg" alt="chi temple steps" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Toaist Temple.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: right;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0329.jpg" alt="chi temple pot" /></p>
<p style="text-align: right;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0333.jpg" alt="chi alter" /></p>
<p style="text-align: right;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0346.jpg" alt="chi smokey roof" /></p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0385.jpg" alt="chi bread sign" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Great flat bread where ever you go!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0386.jpg" alt="chi bread makers" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Tear off a piece with your hands and eat it while it's still hot!</p>

<!--nextpage--></blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0434.jpg" alt="chi market stalls" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Stuffed camel anyone?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0509.jpg" alt="chi turpan hotel" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The Silk Road Turpan Hotel.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">I am traveling with a few dozen eclipse chasers, most of whom I have just met.  But at the ancient citadel at Jiaohe, I spontaneously reunite with people from our chase to Libya in 2006.  Eclipse chasing is one of the few hobbies where you can run into old friends halfway around the world.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0448.jpg" alt="chi jiaohe wide" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Jiaohe.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0461.jpg" alt="chi zands" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Lynn &amp; Louie Zand.  We first met chasing an eclipse in Turkey in 1999.  Now friends for life.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0454.jpg" alt="chi jiaohe dryers" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">They're drying grapes in those huts.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0456.jpg" alt="chi jiaohe path" /></p>
<p style="text-align: right;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0487a.jpg" alt="chi steps" /></p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0469.jpg" alt="chi jiaohe silhouette" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">This is why I love archeological sites in remote locations.  Drama!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">On this expedition, we travel a great deal by bus.  It can become tedious, but it is one of the best ways to see the landscape.  In this case, the vast tundra on the outskirts of the great Gobi desert.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0544.jpg" alt="chi dm highway" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Closer to the eclipse with every mile!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0566.jpg" alt="chi mustard field" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Workers in the never-ending fields of mustard.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0302.jpg" alt="chi toilet" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Sorry.  Can't get used to it.</p>

<!--nextpage--></blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0490.jpg" alt="chi mtn ridge" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">We rest at The Flaming Mountains.  Stunning.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0495.jpg" alt="chi mtn close" /></p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0498.jpg" alt="chi grotto wall" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Fourth century Bezeklik caves and Astana tombs.  Burial grounds for the nobles.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0500.jpg" alt="chi grotto close" /></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">The eclipse is tomorrow.  Our next stop on the Silk Road is Hami - about as remote a locale as you can imagine.  But Hami was a gorgeous, bustling town!  Not what I was expecting!  Full of sights, sounds and smells.</p>
<p style="text-align: right;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0681.jpg" alt="chi hami street1" /></p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0682.jpg" alt="chi hami sellers" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0683.jpg" alt="chi hami tower" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Downtown Hami.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">The Hami Hotel was big and definitely ready for tourists albeit a bit dated in its decor - very old-style Soviet - dank and smoky.  I felt like I was in a 1950s war film.  Some stuff worked, some didn't.  We actually had to bail from one of our room assignments because of the stink.  But no matter!  We're not here for that!</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0686.jpg" alt="chi huddle beer" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Eclipse chaser Jim Huddle relaxes in Hami.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0693.jpg" alt="chi hami post" /></p>
<p style="text-align: right;"><!--nextpage--></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">After dinner, we have a pre-eclipse briefing from Jim Huddle - our eclipse specialist - then back to our rooms to prepare all our photo and observing gear for tomorrow's TSE.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">The night before an eclipse I am pretty tense.  I don't get much sleep.  Especially when I discover one of my video cameras is broken!  But such is the nature of eclipse travel.  I will have to make do with two.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">On eclipse morning, we drive up to Yiwu, the site of the eclipse.  The journey was arduous because of the terrain and too many hours in a bus, and we were stopped three times by military police.  This was one of my biggest problems with China.  The ubiquitous presence of control &amp; law enforcement.  People who live in China are not free.  And neither are we.  The Chinese government controlled every aspect of our eclipse chase, dictating where, when, how and who could see the eclipse.  Each of us were numbered, stamped, checked and re-checked.  For the first time that wonderful, open feeling that comes with eclipse chasing was absent.  Even in Libya the coming together of diverse peoples to share the eclipse had the power to erase national borders and political realities.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0572.jpg" alt="chi bus" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">It's still too small!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0575.jpg" alt="chi dm field" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Hours from an eclipse on the China/Mongolia border!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">The photographing of officials and military police is strictly forbidden.  I didn't want to get entangled with these guys.  But since they stopped our bus so frequently, I couldn't help but steal a shot here and there.  Risky business!</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0577.jpg" alt="chi cop" /></p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0576.jpg" alt="chi cops" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">God knows what they were looking for.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Finally!  The eclipse site!  The whole area was marked with banners and flags.  Dozens of buses were parked and people were marching everywhere.  Of course, as we arrived, an official had to board our bus and give us our ID badges which we had to wear around our necks all day.  Out in the desert it was oppressively hot.  The sun was beating down on the tundra from above and wafts of heat were welling up from the ground below. You couldn't escape the heat.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0582.jpg" alt="chi site flags" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Site of the eclipse in Yiwu.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Still, a few thousand people had gathered here in anticipation of nature's most spectacular event.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0583.jpg" alt="chi malickis" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">More great friends reunite in the Moon's shadow!  Chris &amp; Liz Malicki.</p>

<!--nextpage--></blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0586.jpg" alt="chi eclipse banner" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Exploratorium from San Francisco always does a great live webcast.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0587.jpg" alt="chi eclipse sellers" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Eclipse souvenirs!  But not nearly the merchandise I was expecting for an eclipse in China!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0591.jpg" alt="chi pavillion" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Solar Calendar Chronometer Square.  Built at Yiwu to honour the event.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0601.jpg" alt="chi pavillion close" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0595.jpg" alt="chi sundial" /></p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0597.jpg" alt="chi metal detect" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Metal detectors at an eclipse site is just paranoia!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0599.jpg" alt="chi chasers1" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Chasers from every corner of the globe.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0603.jpg" alt="chi our tents" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Our patch of shade.  Worth more than gold out here.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0604.jpg" alt="chi our tents close" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">40 degrees Celsius in the shade.</p>

<!--nextpage--></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">In the few hours before the eclipse, things start to look bad.  Clouds are building in from the east and the clear sky is disappearing.  And I am not happy with our assigned observing spot.  I need a wide angle view of the approaching shadow but the foreground is obscured by buses and overhead wires.  I have to move.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">I carry all my gear across the desert floor to a spot nearby some eclipse chasers I know from Calgary, Canada.  Within the hour I have my cameras all set up and am happy with the location.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Then Don, the leader of the Calgary expedition, comes over and informs me that I am not welcome to observe the eclipse with his group!  What!??  What the hell?!  So uncool!  And from my own country even!</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">He was very lame at explaining himself, and I never knew why I was not welcome.  But I pack up all my stuff and move across the desert again.  So rare to encounter thoughtless and negative people at an eclipse!</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">By the time I find another suitable place to film from and set up my equipment again, I have a pounding headache.  It's forty degrees  - the air is thick &amp; hot - my head is pounding - and I haven't eaten properly all day.  And I can't get over the Calgary negativity - which is a real bummer.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0609.jpg" alt="chi lonely gear" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">My lonely set up.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">The clouds.  They are getting worse and worse.  As if the day isn't already bad enough, now it is looking like we might be clouded out.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0629.jpg" alt="chi cloudy sky" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">What you don't want to see at an eclipse site!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">At T minus 90 minutes before the eclipse, the Calgary group leaves the site.  They decide at the last minute that their chances of clear skies are better up the highway.  They opt out of this site - pack all their gear - and literally chase the eclipse up the road.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Our group doesn't have the option to re-locate and I have a strange sinking feeling watching 100 people pack up and leave before the eclipse.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">I move again.  I decide I don't want to be out in the desert on my own for this eclipse, so I pack up all my stuff - again - and hump it all back across the desert floor.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0624.jpg" alt="chi scott" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Trooper Scott Gainey!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Arriving back with my group, I explain my filming predicament to Cincinnati Observatory Director Scott Gainey and he offers to help.   We move all the gear forward  - into the clear - and finally set up for good.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0612.jpg" alt="chi dm at site" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Here to stay!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0622.jpg" alt="chi dm looks" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The partial phases are underway. But in and out of clouds!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0628.jpg" alt="chi canright looks" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">David Canright asseses our chances of seeing it.</p>

<!--nextpage--></blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">The partial phase of the eclipse is nearing its end.  Totality is only minutes away and the sun is still hidden behind clouds.  For a few minutes, I thought it was over.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Looking up towards the partially eclipsed Sun in the sky, I notice it is moving slowly towards the bottom of a band of clouds.  Below is clear patch.   Then the Sun bursts out of the clouds rather unannounced and almost blinds me.  Be careful when you look at the Sun dummy! For the next few seconds I am disoriented as I bat my eyes watching a green-coloured sunspot in front of my view.  I have not quite got my vision back when I look up and see the Diamond Ring.  Totality has begun.  And I couldn't be in worse shape!  My pupils are totally shut!  I can still barely see let alone make out any detail in the corona! Damn!</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/anne_totality.jpg" alt="chi anne totality" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The Total Eclipse appears magically in between two bands of clouds!  Photo: Anne Canright.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/dscn8200crop_thin.jpg" alt="chi eclipse thin" /></p>
<p style="text-align: right;"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The crimson-coloured chromosphere is one of the most beautiful phenomenon you can witness during a TSE.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Tim Collins gets these great shots.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/totality_2_500.jpg" alt="chi totality2" /></p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/diamond_1_500.jpg" alt="chi diamond1" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The second Diamond Ring signals the end of totality.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">One minute and fifty-five seconds goes by in a flash - and only towards the end of it do I see any detail in the corona.  Can we do this again?!, I thought.  I had completely screwed up my 10th Total Eclipse.  And In the drama of the moment I realize that I have taken zero pictures.  But at least we saw it!  We came really close to being clouded out on this one.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">But when I review my HD video, I realize I have captured the most amazing sight.  The sequence reveals the entire approach and retreat of the shadow across our location!  It is just stunning!  Never seen anything like it.  Don't miss this film in the Media Vault!</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0646.jpg" alt="chi site group" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The team that made it happen in China in 2008!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: right;"><!--nextpage--></p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0651.jpg" alt="chi dm tahleen" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Eclipse chasers are the coolest folks! New friends.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: justify;">With the eclipse behind us, we travel onward to Dunhuang then leave the bus behind as we fly to Xi'an, then on to Shanghai.</p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0703.jpg" alt="dm buddha" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Dunhuang. There is a massive Buddha carved into the mountain behind me!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0746.jpg" alt="chi xian" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">City of Xi'an</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0758.jpg" alt="chi silhouette sun" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Pagoda style.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0763.jpg" alt="chi silhouette sun cu" /></p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0782.jpg" alt="chi xian wall bikes" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The wall that surrounds the old city in Xi'an.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0780.jpg" alt="chi xian street" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0774.jpg" alt="chi bikes" /></p>
<p style="text-align: right;"><!--nextpage--></p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0854.jpg" alt="chi warriors building" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Site of the Terracotta Warrors in Xi'an</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0810.jpg" alt="chi warriors group" /></p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0813.jpg" alt="chi warriors wide" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The installation is massive.  Very impressive.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0815.jpg" alt="chi warriors rear" /></p>

<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0816.jpg" alt="chi warriors face" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Each warrior is the likeness of a real solider who served the emperor.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0824.jpg" alt="chi warriors broken" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Created circa 246 BC and discovered in 1974.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0826.jpg" alt="chi warriors low" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">More than 8,000 warriors, horses and chariots have been uncovered.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0834a.jpg" alt="chi warriors stand" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">All the warriors face east - except the ones being repaired!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote style="text-align: right;">
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0830.jpg" alt="chi warriors face2" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Intensive restoration work continues.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[The eclipse that went all wrong! But the Terracotta Warriors are awesome.  ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>929</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2008-09-01 09:15:43</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2008-09-01 13:15:43</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>china-01-august-2008</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="tripreport"><![CDATA[Trip Report]]></category>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>_edit_last</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[5]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>post-thumb</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_0830-200x154.jpg]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[631]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[635]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[958]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[883]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[590]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Aruba - 26 February 1998</title>
		<link>http://eclipseguy.com/tripreport/aruba-26-february-1998</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 1998 01:56:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[eclipseguy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://eclipseguy.com/?p=1205</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">My 5th Solar Eclipse
My 4th Successful Total Eclipse in a Row
My first Island Eclipse
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arubatower_500.jpg" alt="aruba tower" /></p>

I was waiting for this one a long time!  My previous eclipse was in India in 1995.  To suffer through 1996 and 1997 with no eclipse was almost too much to bear.  When February 1998 finally came along, I was more than ready for another dose.
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arubabeach_500.jpg" alt="aruba beach" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Your basic island paradise.</p>
</blockquote>
The Aruba eclipse is special for so many reasons.  The island is a Caribbean paradise and the eclipse was in February!  A perfect destination for winter-weary Canadians.  Plus, in the two years prior to this eclipse, I had managed to convince my entire family and a bunch of my friends to come with me.  To share such an inspiring cosmic event with the people closest to me was unforgettable.  And on top of all that, Aruba was where I began filming my documentary about eclipse chasers called Hooked On The Shadow.
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arubadmjon_500_01.jpg" alt="aruba dmjon" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">eclipseguy in Aruba with <strong>Hooked On The Shadow</strong> producer Jon Link.</p>
</blockquote>
It was really easy to co-ordinate an eclipse chase on Aruba because the island is relatively small and the Aruba Tourism Authority did everything they could to help out.  This eclipse was the biggest tourist event in the history of the island - so they took it seriously.  After four or five days of getting used to the weather, I selected an observing site at the southern tip of the island - a place called Baby Beach.  This location was reserved for serious astronomers and I was able to get access for my team.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arubafolks_500.jpg" alt="aruba folks" />

Eclipse chasing with friends and family is the best!</blockquote>
We arrived early in the morning to stake out our private beach front.  In no time we had shade and food and we didn't let the early hour keep us from enjoying Amstel's custom made Eclipse Beer!
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arubadmbeer_500.jpg" alt="aruba dm beer" />

Kudos to Amstel for making an eclipse beer.</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->Before the eclipse began, I spent hours interviewing eclipse chasers and capturing the carnival-like atmosphere on the beach.  I love the buzz before an eclipse!  If you have never experienced this - you don't know what you are missing.  An eclipse is the most intense event you can possibly imagine and the characters it draws from around the world are colourful to say the least.  So passionate about their hobby!
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arubafriends_500.jpg" alt="aruba friends" />

Eclipse chasers!</blockquote>
An hour before the eclipse began the sky clouded over.  Yikes.  Not what eclipse chasers want to see.  The drama is great, but if it goes on too long people start to get very unhappy.  Fortunately, it blew over almost as quickly as it arrived and the pristine Caribbean skies we had heard so much about returned to our site. I breathed a sigh of relief.  I would have been inconsolable if I had brought my family and friends all this way to a cloud out. But the eclipse gods were on my side!  As they were for all the chasers scattered around the Caribbean for this event.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arubapartial_500.jpg" alt="aruba partial" />

Partial eclipse through a pair of binoculars.  Don't ever look through binoculars at a solar eclipse!</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arubadmsp_500.jpg" alt="aruba dmsp" />

eclipseguy talks solar system dynamics with Hooked On The Shadow film editor Sarah Peddie.</blockquote>
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arubapinholes_500.jpg" alt="aruba pinholes" />

A piece of cardboard punched with pinholes betrays the sun in partial eclipse.</blockquote>
You have got to see the video from this eclipse!  Get your copy of Hooked On The Shadow now!
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arubatotality_500.jpg" alt="aruba totality" />

Henry Czerny took this great shot of totality at Baby Beach.</blockquote>
The eclipse was perfect from start to finish.  Incredible location.  Cloudless skies.  Intense, asymmetrical corona adorned by Venus and Jupiter on either side.  A picture can't do justice to the overwhelming effect of a solar eclipse.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arubatotality_wide_500.jpg" alt="aruba totality wide" />

Venus and Jupiter adorn the eclipsed Sun.  Planets and stars are always visible during a TSE.</blockquote>
We bathed in the glory of the umbra for three minutes and thirty-four seconds - a very healthy dose of universal magic.  From Aruba, we all came back changed.
<blockquote><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arubanevis_hat_500.jpg" alt="aruba nevis" />

Next stop:  Turkey, 1999.</blockquote>



<blockquote><img src='http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arubaportraitall_600.jpg' alt='aruba portrait all' />

The team that made it happen in Aruba in 1998! photo Tony Makepeace</blockquote>

]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[My first beach eclipse!  Extra special because we began filming Hooked On The Shadow on this one. ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1205</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>1998-03-26 21:56:38</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>1998-03-27 01:56:38</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>aruba-26-february-1998</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="tripreport"><![CDATA[Trip Report]]></category>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>_edit_last</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[5]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>post-thumb</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/aruba_trip_thumb.jpg]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[614]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[996]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[590]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[883]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>628</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Eclipseguy.com – Eclipse Chasing, Solar Eclipse Videos, Trip Reports, Galleries &raquo; 24 Years of Expeditions]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email></wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://eclipseguy.com/news/20-years-of-expeditions</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>76.9.192.81</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2015-04-12 11:01:17</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2015-04-12 15:01:17</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[[...] Feb 1998 &#8211; Baby Beach, Aruba &#8211; Total -  [...]]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type>pingback</wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>South America - 11 July 2010</title>
		<link>http://eclipseguy.com/tripreport/south-america-%e2%80%93-11-july-2010</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2010 20:52:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[eclipseguy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://eclipseguy.com/?p=1823</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: center;">My 17th Solar Eclipse Expedition</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">My 12th successfully-observed Total Eclipse in a Row<img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/dm_picchu_600_02.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">On the way to Patagonia, I spent two weeks in Peru.  The classic Machu Picchu shot!</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="MsoNormal">I don’t think anyone would argue with me if I said that eclipse chasers really want to see the eclipse.<span> </span>But can we anthropomorphize the eclipse and say, <em>it</em> really wants to be seen?<span> </span></p>
<p class="MsoNormal">The TSE of 11 July 2010 was visible from Tahiti and the surrounding islands – across Easter Island through the south Pacific – ending on the very tip of South America - in Patagonia.<span> </span>Eighteen months before the eclipse, I was booked on a small clipper ship out of Tahiti – we were going to sail the remote Tuamotu Islands of French Polynesia for a week – then see the eclipse in the ocean off Tahiti’s south coast.<span> </span>The perfect plan.<span> </span>I was totally pumped.<span> </span>The idea of sailing around these islands en route to totality was a life dream come true.<span> </span>I love trains.<span> </span>And I love sail boats.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/TSE2010globe_rev_500.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p class="MsoNormal">But no sail ever happened!<span> </span>They cancelled it months in advance.<span> </span>Apparently, the ship operator decided to redeploy the vessel to other, richer waters and dumped 75 chasers from the manifest.<span> </span>Nice.</p>
<p class="MsoNormal">I was then without an eclipse plan.<span> </span>And I let it slide.<span> </span>For months.<span> </span>Pretty soon, all the other Tahiti cruises were sold out.<span> </span>I checked into the tours and the music festival happening on Easter Island – loved the sound of it – but too expensive.<span> </span>(The greed of the tour operators and the airlines early in the selling turned away many people, and in the final few weeks before the eclipse they couldn’t give away their seats. The throngs of people that were supposed to show up on Rapa Nui for this eclipse never materialized).<span> </span>So I booked the next best option – a reasonably priced eclipse flight – a private charter into the path of the eclipse at 35,000 ft.<span> </span>A guaranteed cloudless eclipse!<span> </span>We couldn’t miss!<span> </span>So I booked passage to El Calafate – a sleepy cottage town in Patagonia – where the flight would take off on 11 July 2010.<span> </span></p>
<p class="MsoNormal">But two days before the eclipse – they cancelled the flight.<span> </span>Problems with the aircraft, we were told.<span> </span>I was halfway around the world already and feared I would miss my first Total Eclipse in 20 years.<span> </span></p>
<p class="MsoNormal">But against all odds, the eclipse was seen in a pristine sky above the Andes Mountains.<span> </span>This was the eclipse that wouldn’t take no for an answer.<span> </span></p>
<p><!--nextpage--></p>
<p>And in keeping with my desire to see the whole world while eclipse chasing, I took advantage of the opportunity and booked two weeks in Peru before the eclipse.  Lima - Puno - Cuzco - the Inca Trail - Machu Picchu.  Classic Peru.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/worldmap_peru.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p>The big attraction for me in Peru was the Inca Trail - the famous 4-day hike through the Andes Mountains to the city of Machu Picchu.  I had wanted to do this journey since I was old enough to read.</p>
<p>Entering Peru through the city of Lima, I move straight to Puno.  At 12,500 feet, Puno is one of the highest places on the continent and it's famous because this is where you go to visit Lake Titicaca - the world's highest navigable lake and a critical location in the Inca heritage.</p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4767.jpg" alt="puno" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The city of Puno.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4701.jpg" alt="puno" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">It takes me two days to get over the symptoms of High Altitude Sickness.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">I head out on to Lake Titicaca and visit the floating islands of Uros - where a traditional culture lives on man-made islands, fashioned from the endless supply of reeds growing in the lake.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4724.jpg" alt="uros village" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">It floats!  Islands of Uros in Lake Titicaca.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4722.jpg" alt="uros reeds" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Imagine your house - your floor - your bed - all made out of this.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4727.jpg" alt="uros boat" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Boats too!</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!--nextpage--></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4751.jpg" alt="taquile island" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Agricultural terraces on Taquile.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">The island of Taquile is three hours away by boat.  This remote Quechua  outpost still lives by the traditional Inca values of community  collectivism.  The island is gorgeous - lush - small farms -  agricultural terraces - but the hike to the public square at over 4,000  meters above sea level takes the wind out of me.  Until you have adapted  to the altitude, you can't draw a full breath - and walking uphill is slow and difficult for me.</p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4738.jpg" alt="taquile wheat" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Fields of wheat.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4745.jpg" alt="taquile coca" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Fresh coca leaves can be purchased as easily as a bag of chips.  Helps with the Altitude Sickness...!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4748.jpg" alt="taquile arch" /></p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4753.jpg" alt="taquile steps" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The way down is much easier!</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!--nextpage--></p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4844.jpg" alt="train start" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">I love trains!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The romance of long distance travel by train must be archetypal because I have fallen prey to its influence my entire life.  This one was a real treat - best train journey ever!  I leave Puno - travel through the Peruvian Altiplano and into the Andes that surround Cuzco - my destination.  The ride takes all day - over 10 hours.  En route I witness the most incredible sights - all part of a sparse but vibrant high altitude culture - thriving in the most remote of regions.</p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4823.jpg" alt="train village" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Ancient mountain villages.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4791.jpg" alt="train market" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">As the train passes through, we split the market in two. Inches from the stalls!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4786.jpg" alt="train market 2" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Seconds after we pass, the market swallows up the tracks once again.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4795.jpg" alt="train parts" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Spare parts for your train, sir?</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!--nextpage--></p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4782.jpg" alt="train interior" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">First Class.  Isn't it the only way?  And I was one of only 4 people on the train!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4849.jpg" alt="train dm" /></p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4812.jpg" alt="train sussut" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The Observation Car.  Where I spent most of my time.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4826.jpg" alt="train vista" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">At over 4,300 meters, the peak at La Raya is the highest point on our journey. I felt really lucky to be seeing all this.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4857.jpg" alt="train shadows" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Postcard anyone?</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!--nextpage--></p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4885.jpg" alt="train postcard" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Shall we make it two?  One of my faves.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4830.jpg" alt="train woman" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">A baby alpaca in the arms of its... mother!  The alpaca wool trade is critical to the Peruvian economy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4845.jpg" alt="train end" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">I love trains.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5008.jpg" alt="cuzco wide" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Cuzco.  The Imperial City of the Incas.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">Cuzco is an incredibly busy place.  One gets the sense that it has always been.  As the starting point for hikers on the Inca Trail, it is constantly flooded with backpackers and tourists making their way through town.  But this tourism hasn't pushed the locals away.  As I move around - shoulder to shoulder with the crowds - I pass as many moms with newborns as uniformed school kids as local cart merchants.  There is probably a young hiker couple here from every city in Europe!</p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4976.jpg" alt="cuzco city" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The rainbow flag is the official symbol of Cuzco.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4937.jpg" alt="cuzco cathedral" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Cathedral at the town square.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!--nextpage--></p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4958.jpg" alt="cuzco market" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Hands down Cuzco has the best markets in Peru.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4954.jpg" alt="cuzco textile" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">If you can't stand vibrant colors, endless variety - stay clear!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4985.jpg" alt="cuzco sun temple" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">What's left of the mind-blowing Inca Temple of the Sun or Qorikancha after the Spanish ruined everything.   It is here I begin my wonder with all things Inca.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4988.jpg" alt="cuzco trapezoid" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Inca engineering:  trapezoid windows and doorways.  Aligned, of course.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5000.jpg" alt="cuzco ruins" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The monumental complex of Saqsaywaman, north of Cuzco city.  Meticulously formed boulders put together without mortar.  The Incas were a crafty bunch.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">
<p><!--nextpage--></p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5054.jpg" alt="sacred valley" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The Sacred Valley.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">After a nerve-racking night of trying to pack smartly for my 4-day hike/camp along the Inca Trail (never take more than 5kg!), I make my way through the storied Sacred Valley.  Like something from a history book, this whole region is at once stunning to the eye and overwhelming to the heart.  I stop at several noteworthy sites along the way including Pisac - known for its great Sunday markets.</p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5087.jpg" alt="pisac walls" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The village of Pisac in the Sacred Valley.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5072.jpg" alt="pisac market" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Part of Pisac's extensive markets.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5116.jpg" alt="chapel" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">I came across this chapel with incredible natural light.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5131.jpg" alt="ollantaytambo" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">I overnight in Ollantaytambo before heading out on foot on the Inca Trail.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5144.jpg" alt="ollantaytambo street" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Streets of Ollantaytambo.  The emperor Pachacuti made this town his home. But that was a long time ago.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!--nextpage--></p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5158.jpg" alt="trail start" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Finally!  The start of the great Inca Trail!  I have been waiting for this a long time.  This point is called Kilometer 82.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5163.jpg" alt="inca valley" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Stunning sights await all on this ancient pilgrimage.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5238.jpg" alt="trail path" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Most of what you are walking on is this - rocks and boulders that stretch out for over 40km.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5204.jpg" alt="trail vista 1" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">I frequently have to stop and pinch myself.  Nope.  Not dreaming.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5165.jpg" alt="trail ruins 1" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Amazingly well-preserved agricultural terraces litter this area of the Andes.  A peak into what life was like - long ago.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5218.jpg" alt="trail up " /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The 4-day hike is extremely challenging in places - and not for the timid.  Completely dizzying.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!--nextpage--></p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5194.jpg" alt="trail manuel" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">My private guide, Manuel, spent 5 years on the road to being a Catholic priest.  Eventually, the spirituality of the Incas, his true ancestors, resonated on a much deeper level and he has been a guide for over 10 years.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5177.jpg" alt="trail gear" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">This is what your gear looks like.  Private porters carry the bulk of it - I carried a single knapsack only. That's enough for this terrain!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5211.jpg" alt="trail sellers" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The occasional rest-stop offers hikers the essentials - at a premium.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5175.jpg" alt="trail camp 1" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Our porters setting us up for the night.  The sun set around 6pm each night.  I was crashed by 9pm - latest.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5212.jpg" alt="trail coca" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The real thing.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The coca leaf is revered throughout Peruvian culture for its magical and medicinal qualities.  The lift in spirit and energy that chewing on a few leaves can bring was a most welcome effect in these mountains!  I learned to love it as my Peruvian friends did.  Brought some home, too!  (Shhh.)</p>
<p><!--nextpage--></p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5225.jpg" alt="trail vista 2" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Imagine waking up to this!  Nice to look at - harder to conquer.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5224.jpg" alt="trail peak" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Winded hikers make the final few steps to Dead Woman's Pass after 5 hours of straight, uphill trekking.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5234.jpg" alt="trail top" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Dead Woman's Pass.  This is the tail end of Day 2.  From here to Machu Picchu, the trail descends almost 2,000 meters in altitude.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5292.jpg" alt="trail vista 2" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The stunning beauty of this trail can not be overstated.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5370.jpg" alt="trail drop off" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">It is also dangerous.  If you misstep - it means certain death.  The trail is very uneven and less than a meter wide here.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!--nextpage--></p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5537.jpg" alt="trail sussut walks" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The Incas were hard core.  One is meant to be changed by this approach to Machu Picchu city.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5437.jpg" alt="trail terraces wide" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Inca ruins and agricultural terraces - like this one - can be found daily along the trail.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5271.jpg" alt="trail ruins " /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The chambers, walls &amp; entrances are all aligned with the sky in some way.  Earth's journey around the sun every year was critical to the identity the Incas created for themselves.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5317A.jpg" alt="trail ruins cu" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">I was amazed how we were allowed to explore in intimate detail all the ruins we encountered.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5356.jpg" alt="trail lunch " /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Hikes along the trail are pro all the way.  Your stops are predetermined each day.  Porters are ahead of you - lunch is always ready!  This was the best food of the entire trip.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5447.jpg" alt="trail dark mountains" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">By the end of Day 3 - I am hiking way high in the Andes.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!--nextpage--></p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5411.jpg" alt="trail sussut points" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Am I actually getting used to sights like these?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5413.jpg" alt="trail camp 2" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">We camped here on Day 3.  And I don't even like heights!  I was dizzy the whole time.  Yes - it is straight down beyond that little tree.  Did we bring a flashlight?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5422.jpg" alt="trail camp 2A" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">As the sun set and the fog rolled in, it was obvious:  we were camped in heaven.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5454.jpg" alt="trail vista 3" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Day 4 served up some of the most terrifying parts of the trail.  I actually trembled a few times. That's the Urubamba River.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5514.jpg" alt="machu picchu 1" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">By noon on Day 4, the city of Machu Picchu appears out of the highland jungle.  It is everything you think it is going to be - and then more.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5486.jpg" alt="dm &amp; sussut sungate" /><br />
Me and my excellent hiker pal Sue at the Sun Gate overlooking Machu Picchu city.</p></blockquote>
<p><!--nextpage--></p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5584.jpg" alt="machu picchu 2" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Built by Andean masons in the 1400s, it was unknown to the outside world until 1911.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5653.jpg" alt="machu picchu 3" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">There is a quiet fascination exploring Machu Picchu.  With its massive scale and soaring spirit, it is simply extraordinary.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5588.jpg" alt="mach" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The city is brilliantly conceived with agricultural zones - residential areas - observatories - royal enclosures and temples. Seems like they knew something we don't.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5599.jpg" alt="machu picchu 5" /></p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5600.jpg" alt="machu picchu 6" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">I'd give anything to be here on the solstice on the 21st of June!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5523.jpg" alt="aguas callientes" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Aguas Calientes</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">After the grueling trial of the trail, we final get to relax (and shower!) in Aguas Calientes - the hot springs town at the base of Machu Picchu mountain. This is where I check my email after many days - only to discover my eclipse flight has been canceled.  You're lucky you weren't around when I got this news.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><!--nextpage--><br />
<img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/world_map_buenos.jpg" alt="worldmap buenos" /><br />
What you don't see now is the long journey back to Cuzco - the flight to Lima - the flight down to Buenos Aires - the 10-hour layover in the airport - then the flight to El Calafate in Patagonia at the bottom of Argentina.  I am furious at my eclipse tour company the whole time and not fun to travel with.  If there is no flight - then I am stuck on the ground - and the weather is supposed to be overcast in Calafate - hence the plane idea.  Take my eclipse away from me and watch out.  To make matters worse, we are greeted at the airport by minus 20 degree temperatures and thick ice on the ground.  It was bleak.  With no eclipse on the horizon - what the hell am I doing here?</p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5675.jpg" alt="el calafate" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">El Calafate in Patagonia the morning of the eclipse.  Is that clear sky I see...?</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">Against all good sense, the tour company asks me to pay if I want to come see the eclipse from their ground location.  After leaving me with no flight!  But it's eclipse day already - I am out of options.  I pay.  But I could have strangled them.  I now have just a glimmer of hope that these clear skies will hold out.  That's my focus.  About 150 of us load into these wicked 4x4 trekking machines to haul us up to the top of the Patagonian steppe.  If we stay down in Calafate - the eclipse will set behind the mountains before we can see it.  If this eclipse really does want to be seen - it's down to this machine -</p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5677.jpg" alt="trekker 4x4" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Couldn't stand the tour company.  Loved the ride to the top.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/51_chains.jpg" alt="tire chains" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">As we enter the roughest part of the journey, chains are strapped on to the tires to keep us moving forward through the snow and ice.  Photo: Lukas G.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/55_trekker.jpg" alt="trekker action" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Rough but awesome!  Wait... wasn't I just in Machu Picchu??   Photo: Lukas G.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5700.jpg" alt="trekker 4x4 others" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">At least they seem to know what they're doing on the ground.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5686.jpg" alt="eclipse site" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">What you can't see is the temperature!  Freezing!  Windy as hell!  The tents make it workable.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!--nextpage--></p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5705.jpg" alt="chasers" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The partial phase of the eclipse has begun.  Barely a cloud in the sky.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5698.jpg" alt="chasers 1" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Chasers having fun with safe solar viewing!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5707.jpg" alt="chasers 2" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Stunning location for an eclipse?  I think so.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5712.jpg" alt="dm at eclipse" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Only 4 minutes before the eclipse do I concede:  we're going to see this thing after all!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_5719.jpg" alt="pre eclipse vista" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The scene over the Andes - seconds before the shadow of the Moon arrives.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/wide_500.jpg" alt="totality wide" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Embrace of the Shadow.  Lukas G. captures this amazing image of the shadow cone seemingly reaching out from beyond the mountains.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!--nextpage--></p>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/totality_600.jpg" alt="totality el calafate" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Hovering over the Andes in the distance  -  this is the lowest eclipse I have ever seen.  And a golden corona!  Another first!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/diamond_600.jpg" alt="diamond el calafate" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">It lasts 2:40 - but feels like 10 seconds.  The Diamond Ring at 3rd contact.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/shadow_sky.jpg" alt="shadow in sky" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Seconds later we see the sky cut in half by the umbra.  Total Eclipse to the right; no Total Eclipse to the left.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">
<p style="text-align: left;">Success sure is sweet!  But I could have done without all the drama in the last few days.  But that is what eclipse chasers deal with.  I would do it all again.  This really was the eclipse that wouldn't take no for an answer.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Wanna come next time?</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[The eclipse in Patagonia that wouldn’t take no for an answer.  Huge report!  Tons of pix here!!  Go get a sandwich and come back.  ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1823</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2010-08-01 16:52:48</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2010-08-01 20:52:48</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>south-america-%e2%80%93-11-july-2010</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="tripreport"><![CDATA[Trip Report]]></category>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>_edit_last</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[5]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>post-thumb</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/patagonia_report_thumb11.jpg]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[1795]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[1574]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[981]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[883]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[590]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Arizona - May 20, 2012</title>
		<link>http://eclipseguy.com/tripreport/arizona-may-20-2012</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 17 Feb 2013 04:03:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[eclipseguy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://eclipseguy.com/?p=2500</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;">My 18th Solar Eclipse Expedition
My second successfully-observed Annular Eclipse!</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="aligncenter" alt="dm in the field1" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00607A_01.jpg" /></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">This is what my Front Row Seat on the Universe looked like in Arizona in May 2012!</p>
<a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arizona_location.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-2708 aligncenter" alt="arizona_location" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arizona_location.jpg" width="600" height="450" /></a>
<p style="text-align: center;">The region around Grand Canyon National Park is an ideal eclipse location on the Earth.  Sunny and dry.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/video/beads-in-arizona">10 minute documentary film from this eclipse</a></p>
&nbsp;
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00092A.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-2671 aligncenter" alt="DSC00092A" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00092A.jpg" width="601" height="450" /></a>The mystique of the American southwest has always called to me.  This is my first experience in the Grand Canyon, and it did not disappoint!</p>
</blockquote>
I decided only a week before to chase this eclipse!  Was saving my dimes for the Total Eclipse in Australia later in the year.  And even though I do nothing but globe-trot to exotic locales - it does get expensive! But I made it happen.  And I was so richly rewarded for doing so.  The <a href="http://eclipseguy.com/video/beads-in-arizona">documentary film</a> that come out of this expedition is worth every penny it cost me. <!--nextpage-->
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00032A.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2673" alt="DSC00032A" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00032A.jpg" width="601" height="450" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00049A.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2674" alt="DSC00049A" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00049A.jpg" width="601" height="450" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">I'm filming with my new video camera on this trip.  The <a href="http://eclipseguy.com/video/beads-in-arizona">documentary film</a> I made of this eclipse is a must-see!</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00079A.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2675" alt="DSC00079A" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00079A.jpg" width="601" height="450" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">The Colorado River is the culprit here!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00083A.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2676" alt="DSC00083A" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00083A.jpg" width="409" height="544" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">Eclipse chasers Chris and Liz Malicki.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00094A.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2678" alt="DSC00094A" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00094A.jpg" width="601" height="450" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">Photography gets me excited.</p>
</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00658A.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2681" alt="DSC00658A" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00658A.jpg" width="601" height="450" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00657A.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2680" alt="DSC00657A" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00657A.jpg" width="601" height="450" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00652A.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2679" alt="DSC00652A" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00652A.jpg" width="600" height="298" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">All Sedona, all the time.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00109A.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2682" alt="DSC00109A" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00109A.jpg" width="601" height="450" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">This is my eclipse day T!  Only put it on 18 times!  That's right - it's the Days Inn in Flagstaff.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00628A.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2687" alt="DSC00628A" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00628A.jpg" width="601" height="450" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">Chris Malicki watching the beginning of the eclipse.</p>
</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
<p style="text-align: left;">We chose a very specific GPS location as our observing site this time.  Just inside the southern limit of the eclipse path, we are able to see certain phenomenon not visible from the centre line.  These 'Baily's Beads' occur only when the edge of the Moon grazes the edge of the Sun.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arizona-edge-path.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-2726 aligncenter" alt="arizona edge path" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arizona-edge-path.jpg" width="600" height="450" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/annular_1.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2689" alt="annular_1" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/annular_1.jpg" width="600" height="450" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">As the Moon slides across the face of the Sun from bottom right to top left, you can easily see that the Moon's disc is slightly smaller than the Sun's.   That's why today's eclipse is not Total.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00613A.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2685" alt="DSC00613A" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00613A.jpg" width="601" height="450" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">Allan Connery doesn't miss a second of the action with his pro eclipse viewers!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/annular_2.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2690" alt="annular_2" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/annular_2.jpg" width="600" height="450" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">As the Moon slides upward, it's clear we are near the edge of the path.  Very exciting!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00610A.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2684" alt="DSC00610A" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00610A.jpg" width="601" height="450" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/annular_ring.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2695" alt="annular_ring" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/annular_ring.jpg" width="600" height="450" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">The super-thin ring of an annular eclipse at the southern edge.  Beads abound where the Moon's edge grazes the Sun's at top right. <a href="http://eclipseguy.com/video/beads-in-arizona">See the film here!</a></p>
</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00614A.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2686" alt="DSC00614A" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00614A.jpg" width="601" height="450" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">Chris gets up close and personal with the annular eclipse through his trusty scope.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/annular_4.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2691" alt="annular_4" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/annular_4.jpg" width="600" height="450" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">The Moon continues its upward climb and breaks the ring.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/newspaper-shot.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2728" alt="newspaper shot" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/newspaper-shot.jpg" width="600" height="417" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The Arizona Republic's Michael Chow captures this magical image of a few hikers in the right place, at the right time.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSCN4408A.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2693" alt="DSCN4408A" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSCN4408A.jpg" width="601" height="450" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">Whoohoo!  This is WAY better than golf!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00629A.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2688" alt="DSC00629A" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00629A.jpg" width="601" height="450" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">Eclipse chasers May 20, 2012.  Liz Malicki, Chris Malicki, Allan Connery, Val Connery, eclipseguy.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"></p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/partial_sunset.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2694" alt="partial_sunset" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/partial_sunset.jpg" width="600" height="450" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">One of my favourite eclipse images of all time.  The still-partially-eclipsed sun setting over the desert horizon.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">Tired of the razor-thin superficiality of your existence?  All done with reality shows and fatty foods?  Come eclipse chasing with me.  <a href=" http://eclipseguy.com/eclipse-calendar">See where we are going next.</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[The last-minute eclipse chase steeped in the mystique of the American southwest.  It don't get no betta!]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>2500</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-02-17 00:03:48</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-02-17 04:03:48</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>arizona-may-20-2012</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="tripreport"><![CDATA[Trip Report]]></category>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>_edit_last</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[5]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>post-thumb</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/arizona_gallery_thumb.jpg]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[2443]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[658]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[2594]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[981]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[883]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[1750]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By Air above The Norwegian Sea - 20 March 2015</title>
		<link>http://eclipseguy.com/tripreport/by-air-above-the-norwegian-sea-20-march-2015</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Apr 2015 20:55:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[eclipseguy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://eclipseguy.com/?p=2966</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>My 21st Solar Eclipse Expedition</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>My 14th Total Eclipse of the Sun</strong></p>

<blockquote><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/tse2015-globe-view1.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-2969 aligncenter" alt="tse2015 globe view1" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/tse2015-globe-view1.jpg" width="600" height="399" /></a>
<p style="text-align: center;"> My first Total Eclipse from a plane!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/TSE2015_flightpath.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-2845 aligncenter" alt="TSE2015_flightpath" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/TSE2015_flightpath.jpg" width="500" height="572" /></a>Dusseldorf to Dusseldorf - via the best view in the world!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00834.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-2972 aligncenter" alt="DSC00834" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00834.jpg" width="640" height="427" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">We check in about 6am for our special flight to totality. There are over 15 eclipse flights today!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00836.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2973" alt="DSC00836" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00836.jpg" width="640" height="427" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Veteran chasers get boarding passes after years of planning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00841.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2974" alt="DSC00841" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00841.jpg" width="640" height="497" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Pretty stoked to see my 21st eclipse!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00842.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2975 aligncenter" alt="DSC00842" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00842.jpg" width="640" height="427" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">This is my first trip to a Point that doesn't exist!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00867.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-2976 aligncenter" alt="DSC00867" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00867.jpg" width="640" height="477" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">eclipseguy with Glenn Schneider from The Steward Observatory at the University of Arizona. Glenn is the Project Lead - he makes the calculations for our Totality Run: the aircraft's interception of the Moon's umbra.  He's seen 32 Total Solar Eclipses!</p>
</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00868.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-2978 aligncenter" alt="DSC00868" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/DSC00868.jpg" width="640" height="440" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">This is the Boeing 737-800 taking us to 37,000 ft.</p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/sofi2015-08.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3014" alt="sofi2015-08" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/sofi2015-08.jpg" width="600" height="400" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">High tech stabilization techniques!</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Frame Grabs from the Video</strong></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Screen-Shot-2015-03-30-at-6.45.15-PM.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-2979 aligncenter" alt="Screen Shot 2015-03-30 at 6.45.15 PM" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Screen-Shot-2015-03-30-at-6.45.15-PM.png" width="600" height="339" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Look how much room we have!  I love flying like this.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Screen-Shot-2015-03-30-at-6.43.26-PM.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-2980 aligncenter" alt="Screen Shot 2015-03-30 at 6.43.26 PM" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Screen-Shot-2015-03-30-at-6.43.26-PM.png" width="600" height="335" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Chasers invent all kinds of specialized gear to shoot totality from up here.  The restraints are considerable!</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Screen-Shot-2015-03-30-at-6.44.30-PM.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-2981 aligncenter" alt="Screen Shot 2015-03-30 at 6.44.30 PM" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Screen-Shot-2015-03-30-at-6.44.30-PM.png" width="600" height="335" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Screen-Shot-2015-03-30-at-6.46.46-PM.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-2982 aligncenter" alt="Screen Shot 2015-03-30 at 6.46.46 PM" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Screen-Shot-2015-03-30-at-6.46.46-PM.png" width="600" height="337" /></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3016" alt="sofi2015-27" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/sofi2015-27.jpg" width="300" height="330" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Screen-Shot-2015-03-30-at-6.48.04-PM.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-2983 aligncenter" alt="Screen Shot 2015-03-30 at 6.48.04 PM" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Screen-Shot-2015-03-30-at-6.48.04-PM.png" width="600" height="336" /></a>You can see increased detail in the solar corona if you 'dark adapt' your dominant eye before totality begins.  There were lots of pirates on board!</p>
</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
<p style="text-align: left;">Over a lifetime of eclipse chasing, it's not uncommon to have a few eclipses that are missed because of bad weather or equipment failure or any of the other contingencies that fall under Murphy's Law.  And I have been very lucky!  I always see the eclipse and my shots always turn out.  But I am a little disappointed with my images from the GoPro camera I mounted at the window in Row 12.  Ice Crystals built up as we climbed higher and drew closer to totality.  By our Totality Run, there was almost no space on the window that didn't look like I was shooting through a heavy sprinkling of icing sugar. Gulp.  As a result, the images are all dirty - something we tried hard to avoid by cleaning the windows thoroughly on the ground.  But they are all I've got!  Still, the incredible and almost frightening approach of the Moon's shadow from behind us is still discernible.</p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/gopro_1.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-2984 aligncenter" alt="gopro_1" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/gopro_1.png" width="600" height="338" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">At 37,000 ft. above the North Sea between Norway and Iceland, the aircraft positions itself precisely in the same direction of travel as the advancing umbral shadow that is being projected on to the Earth by the eclipsing Moon.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/gopro_2.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-2985 aligncenter" alt="gopro_2" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/gopro_2.png" width="600" height="338" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">As totality nears, you can clearly see the darkening on the horizon to the south as the monstrous, dark shadow of the Moon races to engulf us from behind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/gopro_3.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-2986 aligncenter" alt="gopro_3" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/gopro_3.png" width="600" height="338" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">At the precise moment predicted, the advancing edge of the Moon's shadow is projected on to the Earth at our location.  Totality begins!  And a full set of goosebumps to boot!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/gopro_4.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-2987 aligncenter" alt="gopro_4" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/gopro_4.png" width="600" height="339" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">At mid-totality, the curved aspect of the shadow is evident as it extends through the sky.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/gopro_5.png"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2988 aligncenter" alt="gopro_5" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/gopro_5.png" width="600" height="338" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Traveling at about 3,000 kph., the Moon's shadow inevitably overtakes us, and the trailing edge of the shadow cone can now be seen beneath us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/gopro_6.png"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2989 aligncenter" alt="gopro_6" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/gopro_6.png" width="600" height="338" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Totality ends with the reappearance of the Sun's photosphere, and the trailing edge of the umbra can be seen racing off towards Svalbard and the North Pole.</p>
</blockquote>
<!--nextpage-->
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/TSE2015_1.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-2991 aligncenter" alt="TSE2015_1" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/TSE2015_1.jpg" width="600" height="399" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">My frame-grab of the Diamond Ring that starts totality!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/TSE2015_2.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-2992 aligncenter" alt="TSE2015_2" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/TSE2015_2.jpg" width="600" height="399" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Mid-Totality and the corona at its peak.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/sofi2015-15.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3015" alt="sofi2015-15" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/sofi2015-15.jpg" width="600" height="400" /></a></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Screen-Shot-2015-03-30-at-6.55.51-PM.png"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2993 aligncenter" alt="Screen Shot 2015-03-30 at 6.55.51 PM" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Screen-Shot-2015-03-30-at-6.55.51-PM.png" width="600" height="336" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">When its over its time for champagne and the unveiling of Craig Small's eclipse flag, a sign that bodes well for clear skies at the next eclipse!</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_3486A.jpg"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-3033" alt="IMG_3486A" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/IMG_3486A.jpg" width="600" height="400" /></a></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Screen-Shot-2015-03-30-at-6.49.30-PM.png"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2994 aligncenter" alt="Screen Shot 2015-03-30 at 6.49.30 PM" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Screen-Shot-2015-03-30-at-6.49.30-PM.png" width="600" height="338" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">A most curious flight plan!  The straight edge of the flight path to the west was our Totality Run.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="size-full wp-image-2953 aligncenter" alt="TSE_2015_GROUP_PHOTO_600" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/TSE_2015_GROUP_PHOTO_600.jpeg" width="600" height="235" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">The team that made it happen on 20 March 2015.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Malicki_totality_600.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-2995 aligncenter" alt="Malicki_totality_600" src="http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/Malicki_totality_600.jpg" width="600" height="399" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Chris Malicki shared Row 12 with me and got this great image.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align: left;">There were scores of great images and videos to come out of this eclipse - from the air and from land.  Check out these additional reports from chasers around the world.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://nicmosis.as.arizona.edu:8000/ECLIPSE_WEB/TSE2015/TSE2015_REPORT.html" target="_blank">Glenn Schneider's report</a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://sites.williams.edu/iau-eclipses/svalbard-eclipse-2015/" target="_blank">Williams College Expedition Svalbard</a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://www.twanight.org/newTWAN/photos.asp?ID=3004990" target="_blank">Tunc Tezel Photo</a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://www.eclipseland.com/europa-2015-total.html" target="_blank">Stephan Hiensius Eclipseland</a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="https://skyweek.wordpress.com/2015/03/19/live-blog-zur-sonnenfinsternis-vom-20-marz/" target="_blank">Daniel Fisher Blog1</a>  <a href="https://skyweek.wordpress.com/2015/03/23/nova-sgr-2015-no-2-erreichte-4-mag-fallt-nun/" target="_blank">Daniel Fisher Blog2</a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="https://vimeo.com/122849251" target="_blank">Martin Junius Video</a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Yjibg3jWx_4&amp;feature=youtu.be" target="_blank">Guillaume Cannat Video</a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://apod.nasa.gov/apod/ap150331.html" target="_blank">Composite Photo of the Corona March 20, 2015</a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://nordlandseite.de/berichte/reise/sonnenfinsternis2015.htm" target="_blank">Thomas Bujack Report</a>  Thanks for the pictures!</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Wanna come eclipse chasing?  <a href="http://eclipseguy.com/eclipse-calendar">See where we are headed next</a>.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"></p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[The monstrous black shadow stuns chasers at 37,000 ft with never-before-seen views. At 600 mph this is eclipse chasing! ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>2966</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2015-04-11 16:55:37</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2015-04-11 20:55:37</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>by-air-above-the-norwegian-sea-20-march-2015</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="tripreport"><![CDATA[Trip Report]]></category>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>_edit_last</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[5]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>post-thumb</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[http://eclipseguy.com/wp-content/uploads/tse-2015-web-thumb2.png]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[1795]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[2443]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[2594]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[981]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[883]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<egpostmeta>
			<meta_key>vid-related</meta_key>
			<meta_value><![CDATA[590]]></meta_value>
		</egpostmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>624</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Eclipseguy.com – Eclipse Chasing, Solar Eclipse Videos, Trip Reports, Galleries &raquo; Success at 37,000 ft. above the North Sea!]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email></wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://eclipseguy.com/news/success-at-37000-ft-above-the-north-sea</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>76.9.192.81</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2015-04-11 19:18:35</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2015-04-11 23:18:35</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[[...] Read the Trip Report here. [...]]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type>pingback</wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
</channel>
</rss>
